<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A review of Doctor Bramble, late Bishop of Londenderry, his Faire warning against the Scotes disciplin by R.B.G.</title>
            <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10694</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11992462</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11992462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 80:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A review of Doctor Bramble, late Bishop of Londenderry, his Faire warning against the Scotes disciplin by R.B.G.</title>
                  <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 91, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Michael Stael ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Delf :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Robert Baillie. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bramhall, John, 1594-1663. --  Fair warning to take heed of the Scotish discipline.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52046:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REVIEW OF DOCTOR BRAMBLE, Late Bishop of LONDENDERRY, <hi>HIS</hi> FAIRE WARNING Againſt the Scotes Diſciplin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By R. B. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at DELF, By <hi>Michiel Stael,</hi> dwelling at the Turf-Market 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52046:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52046:2"/>
            <head>For the right Honourable the Noble and potent Lord <hi>JOHN</hi> Earle of Caſſils, Lord <hi>KENNEDY,</hi> &amp;c. one of his <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> privie counſel, and Lord Iuſtice gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of Scotland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y long experience of your Lordships ſinceer zeale to the truth of God, and affection to the liberties of the Church and Kingdome of Scotland, againſt all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies whomſoever; hath imboldened me to offer by your Lordships hand to the view of the publick, my following anſwer to a very bitter enemy of that Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for their adhaerence to the ſacred truth of God and their own juſt liberties.</p>
            <p>At my firſt ſight of his Book and many dayes thereafter I had no purpoſe at all to medle with him:
<note place="margin">The Authors reaſons of his wryting.</note> your Lordſhip knowes how unprovided men of my preſent condition muſt be, either with leaſure, or accommodations, or a minde ſuitable for wryting of books. Alſo <hi>Doctor Bramble</hi> was ſo well knowne on the other ſide of the Sea, the juſtice of the Parliament of England and Scotland having unanimouſly condemned him to ſtand upon the higheſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of infamy, among the firſt of the unpardonable incendiaries, and in the head of the moſt pernicious inſtruments of the late miſeries in Britaine and Ireland: and the evident falshood of his calumnies were ſo clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed long ago in printed anſwers to the infamous Authors whence he had borrowed them; I ſaw laſtly the mans Spirit ſo extreame ſaucy, and his pen ſo weſpiſh and full of gall, that I judged him unworthy of any anſwer. But underſtanding his malions boldnes to put his Book in the hand of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> of the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> and al the eminent perſonages of this place who can reed Engliſh; yea to ſend it abroad unto all the Univerſities of theſe Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with very high and inſinuating commendations, from the prime favourers of the Epiſcopall cauſe: hearing alſo the threats of that faction to put this their Excellent and unanſwerable peece, both in Dutch, Frenſh, and Latine; that in the whole neighbouring World the reputation of the Scotes might thereby be wounded, killed, and buried, without hope of recovery; I found it neceſſary, at the deſire of diverſe friends, to ſend this my review after it, hoping that all who ſhall be pleaſed to be at the paines of comparing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the challenge, may be induced to pronounce him not only a raſh, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timous, malicious, but alſo a very falſe accuſer. This much juſtice doe I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from every judicious and aequitable comparer of our wrytes, upon the hazard of their cenſure to fall upon my ſide.
<note place="margin">The Praelats are unable by reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.</note>
            </p>
            <p>His invectives againſt us are chiefly for three things; our Diſcipline, our Covenant, our alleadged unkindnes to our late Soveraigne. My apology for the firſt is that in diſciplin we maintaine no conſiderable concluſion, but what
<pb facs="tcp:52046:3"/>is avowed by all the Reformed Churches, eſpecially our Brethren of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as by the approbatory ſuffrages of the Univerſities of <hi>Leyden, Vtrecht</hi> and others, to the theorems whereupon our adverſarie doth build his chief accuſations, may appeare. If our practiſe had aberred from the common rule, the crookednes of the one ought not to praejudge the ſtraightnes of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: though what our adverſary alleadgeth of theſe aberrations is nothing, but his owne calumnious imputations: the chiefe quarrel is our rule it ſelfe, which all the reformed harmoniouſly defend with us, to bee according to Scripture; and the Epiſcopall declinations, to bee beſide and againſt the line of the word, yea Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p>If our Praelats had found the humour of diſputing this maine cauſe to ſtir in their veines, why did they not vent it in replyes to Didoclavius and Gerſome Bucerus, who for long thirty yeares have ſtood unanſwered? or if freſher meats had more pleaſed their taſt, why did not their ſtomacks venture on <hi>Salmaſius</hi> or Hondels books againſt Epiſcopacy? If verbal debates had liked them better then wryting, why had none of them the courage to accept the conference, with that incomparably moſt learned of all knights now living or in any bygone age Sir <hi>Claud Somayis;</hi> who by a perſon of honour about the King, did ſignify his readines to prove before his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> againſt any one or all his praelaticall divines, that their Epiſcopacy had no warrant at all in the word of God, or any good reaſon?</p>
            <p>But our friends are much wiſer then to be at the trouble and hazard of any ſuch exerciſe;
<note place="margin">Their ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are trucks of Court.</note> the artifices of the court are their old trade, they know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how to watch the ſeaſons, and to diſtribute amongſt themſelves the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the Kings opportunities, when privatly without contradiction they may inſtill in his tender mind their corrupt principles, and inſtruct him in his cabine, how ſafe it is for his conſcience, and how much for his honor ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ruine himſelfe, his family and all his Kingdomes with his own hands, then to deſert the holy Church, that is the Biſhops and their followers; then to joine with the rebellious Covenanters, enemies to God, to his Father, to to Monarchy: that the embracing of the Barbarous Iriſh the pardoning of all their monſtruous murders, the rewarding of their expected merits with a free liberty of Popery, and acceſſe to all places of the higheſt truſt, though contrary to all the Lawes which England and Ireland has knowne this hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares; all this without and before any Parliament, muſt be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, with conſcience, honor and all good reaſon. Yea to bind up the ſoule of the moſt ſweet and ingenuous of Princes, in their chaines of their ſlavery for ever, they have fallen upon a moſt rare trick, which hardly the inventions of all their praedeceſſors can pararel.
<note place="margin">The Brothers unlu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foot is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> They reſt not ſatisfied, that for the upholding of their ambition and greed, they did harden our late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne to his very laſt in their Errours, and without compaſſion did dryve him on to his fatal praecipice; unles they make him continue after his death to cry loud every day in the cares of his Son in his later will and teſtament,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to follow him in that ſame way of ruine; rather then to give over to ſerve the luſts of the praelaticall clergy. They have gathered together his <hi>Majeſties</hi> laſt papers, and cut of them have made a book, whereupon their beſt pens
<pb facs="tcp:52046:3"/>have dropped the greateſt eloqution, reaſon and devotion was among them, by way of eſſayes; as it were to frame the heart of the Son by the fingers of the dying Father to piety, wiſedome, patience, and every virtue; but ever &amp; znone to let fall ſo much of their own ungracious dew, as may irrigat the feeds of their praelaticall Errors and Church intereſt; ſo farre as to charge him to perſeveer in the maintainance of Epiſcopall governement upon all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, without the change of any thing except a little p. 278. and to aſſure that all Covenanters are of a faction engaged into a Religious rebellion, who may never be truſted till they have repented of their Covenant; and that till then never leſſe loyalty juſtice or humanity may be expected from any, then from them; that if hee ſtand in need of them hee is undone, for they will devoure him as the Serpent does the dove.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like pernicious maximes framed by an Epiſcopall hand, of purpoſe to ſeparat for ever the King from all his covenanted ſubjects, how farr they were from the heart, language and wrytings of our late Soveraigne, all who were aquainted with his carriage and moſt intime affections at New-Caſtle, in the Iſle of Wight and thereafter, can teſtify, But it is reaſon when the Praelats doe frame an image of a King that they ſhould have liberty to place their owne image in its forheade, as the ſtatuary of old did his, in the <hi>Boſs</hi> of <hi>Pallas</hi> targe, with ſuch artifice that all her worſhipers were neceſſitat to worſhip him and that no hand was able to deſtroy the one without the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folution and breaking in peeces of the other; yet our Praelats would know, that in this age there be many excellent Engyneers, whoſe witty practicks tranſcend the moſt skilfull experiments of our Aunceſtors: and what ever may be the ignorance or weaknes of men, wee truſt the breath of our Lords mouth will not faile to blow out the Bishop from the Kings armes, without any detriment at all to royalty, Allwayes the wicked and impious cunning of theſe craftſemen is much to be blamed who dare be bold to inſert and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave themſelfes ſo deeply in the images of the Gods as the one cannot be intended to be picked out of the other more then the Aple from the eye, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the ſubſiſtance of both be put in hazard.</p>
            <p>The other matter of his rayling againſt us is the ſolemne league and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;
<note place="margin">The only crime of the Covenant, is that it extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate praelacy.</note> when this nimble and quick enough Doctor comes aſſiſted with all the reaſons the whole Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> can afford him, to demonſtrat it as he profeſſes in his laſt Chapter, to be wicked, falſe, void, and what not; wee find his moſt demonſtrative proofes to be ſo poor and ſilly that they infere nothing of his concluſion. To this day no man has ſhewed any errour in the mater of that covenant; as for our framing and taking of it, our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries drave us thereunto, with a great deale of neceſſity; and now being in it, neither their fraud nor force may bring us from it againe, for we feare the oath of God. After much deliberation we found that covenant the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne meanes to joyne and keep together the whole orthodox party in the three Kingdomes, for the defence of their Religion and Liberties which a popish, praelaticall and malignant faction with all their might were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning who ſtill to this day are going on in the ſame deſigne, without any viſible change, in the moſt of their former principles. And why ſhould any
<pb facs="tcp:52046:4"/>who loves the King hate this covenant, which is the ſtrayteſtty the world can deviſe, to knit all to him and his poſterity, if ſo be his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> might be pleaſed to enter therein; but by all meanes ſuch a miſchiefe muſt be aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for ſo the roote of Epiſcopacy would quickly wither without any hope of repullulation; an evill farr greater in the thoughts of them who now mannage the conſcience of the Court the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the extirpation of Monarchy the everſion of all the three Kingdomes or any other earthly miſery.</p>
            <p>As for the third ſubject of the Warners fury againſt us,
<note place="margin">The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are moſt juſtly caſt out of England.</note> our unkindnes to the late King, if any truth were in this falſe challenge, no other creature on earth could be ſuppoſed the true cauſe thereof, but our unhappy praelats: all our grievances both of Church and State, firſt and laſt, came princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally from them: had they never been authors of any more miſchiefe, then what they occaſioned to our late Soveraigne, his perſon, family and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions this laſt dozn of yeares, there is abundant reaſon of burying that their praeter and Antiſcripturall order in the grave of perpetuall infamy. But the truth is, beſide more auncient quarrels, ſince the dayes of our fathers the Albigenſes, this limb of Antichriſt has ever been witneſſed againſt; Wickleif, Huſs, and their followers were zealous in this charge, till Luther and his diſciples got it flung out of all the reformed world, except England; where the violence of the ill adviſed princes did keep it up for the perpetuall trouble of that land, till now at laſt it hath well neare kicked downe to the ground there,
<note place="margin">The Scots were never injurious to their King.</note> both Church and Kingdome. As for the point in hand we deny all unkindnes to our King whereof any reaſonable complaint can be framed againſt us. Our firſt conteſts ſtand juſtified this day by King and Parliament in both Kingdomes. When his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> was ſo ill adviſed as to bring downe upon our borders an English army for to punish our refuſing of a world of novations in our Religion contrary to the lawes of God and of our country, what could our land doe leſſe then lie downe in their armes upon Dunce law for their juſt and neceſſary defence? when it was in their power with eaſe to haue diſſipat the oppoſit army, they ſhew themſelves moſt ready upon very eaſy conditions to goe home in peace, and gladly would have reſted there, had not the furious Biſhops moved his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> without all provocation, to breake that firſt peace and make for a ſecond invaſion of Scotland, only to ſecond their unreaſonable rage: was it not then neceſſary for the Scots to arme againe? when they had deſeate the Epiſcopall Army and taken New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle though they found nothing conſiderable to ſtand in their way to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, yet they were content to lie ſtill in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and upon very meane tearnes to returne the ſecond time in peace. For all this the praelats could not give it over, but raiſed a new Army and filled England with fire and ſword, yea well neere ſubdued the Parliament and their followers and did almoſt accompliſh their firſt deſignes upon the whole Iſle. The Scots then with moſt earneſt and pitifull entreaties were called upon by their Brethren of England for helpe, where unwilling that their brethren ſhould periſh in their ſight and a bridge ſhould be made over their carcaſſes for a third warre upon Scotland, when after long tryall they had found all their interceſſions with the King for a moderat and reaſonable accommodation
<pb facs="tcp:52046:4"/>ſlighted and rejected they ſuffered themſelves to be perſwaded to enter in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with their oppreſſed and fainting brethren, for the mantainance of the common cauſe of Religion and liberty, but with expreſſe Articles for the preſervation of royalty in all its juſt rights in his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and his poſterity; what unkindnes was heer in the Scots to their King?</p>
            <p>When by Gods bleſſing on the Scotes helpe the oppoſit faction was fully ſubdued, his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> left <hi>Oxford</hi> with a purpoſe for <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Scotes ſelling of the King is a moſt falſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie.</note> but by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ordinances againſt his receivers, he diverted towards <hi>Linn,</hi> to ship for <hi>Holland</hi> or <hi>France;</hi> where by the way fearing a diſcovery and ſurpriſe, he was neceſſitate to caſt himſelfe upon the Scotes army at <hi>New-wark;</hi> upon his promiſe to give ſatisfaction to the propoſitions of both Kingdomes, he was received there and to <hi>New-caſtle:</hi> here his old oathes to adhaere unto Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy hindred him to give the expected ſatiſfaction. AT that time the prime leaders of the Engliſh army were ſeeking with all earneſtnes occaſion to fall upon the Scots, much out of heart and reputation by <hi>Iames Grahame</hi> and his <hi>Irishes</hi> incurſions, moſt unhappy for the Kings affaires: Scotland at that time was ſo full of diviſions that if the King had gone thither they were in an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hazard of a preſent war both within among themſelfes, and without from England: our friends in the Engliſh Parliament whom we did, and had reaſon to truſt, aſſured us that our taking the King with us to Scotland, was the keeping of the Sectarian Army on foot, for the wracke of the King, of Scorland, of the Presbyterian party in England; as the ſending of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie</hi> to one of his houſes neer London,, upon the faith of the Parliament of England, was the only way to get the Sectaryes diſarmed, the King and the people ſettled in a peace, upon ſuch tearmes as ſhould be ſatisfactory both to the King and the Scots and all the wel-affected in England. This being the true caſe was it any, either unjuſtice, unkindnes or imprudence in the Scots to leave the King with his Parliament of England? was this a ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him to his enemies? the monyes the Scots received at their departure out of England had no relation at all to the King, they were ſcarce the ſixth parte of the arreares due to them for bygon ſervice; they were but the one halfe of the ſume capitulat for, not only without any reference to the King, but by an act of the Engliſh Parliament excluding expreſly from that Treaty of the armies departure all conſideration of the diſpoſall of the Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The unexpected evills that followed in the Armies rebellion, in their ſeaſing on London, deſtroying the Parliament, murthering the King, no mortall eye could have forſeen. The Scots were ever ready to the utmoſt of their power to have prevented all theſe miſchiefes with the hazard of what was deareſt to them; notwithſtanding of all the hard meaſure they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten received both from the King and the moſt of their friends in England. That they did not in time and unanimouſly ſtur to purpoſe for theſe ends they are to anſwer it to God, who were the true Authors; the innocency of the Church is cleered in the following treatiſe. Among the many cauſes of theſe miſeries the prime fountaine was the venome of Epiſcopall principles which ſome ſerpents conſtantly did infuſe by their ſpeaches and letters in the eares and heart of the King to keep him of from giving that ſatisfaction to
<pb facs="tcp:52046:5"/>his good ſubjects which they found moſt neceſſary and due; the very ſame cauſe which ties up this day the hands of covenanters from redreſſing all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſorders could they have the King to joyne with them in their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to quit his unhappy Biſhops, to lay aſide his formall and dead Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, to caſt himſelfe upon the counſels of his Parliaments it were eaſy to prophecie what quickly would become of all his enemies: but ſo long as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall and malignant agents compaſſeth him about (though all that comes neer may ſee him as lovely hopfull, and promiſing a prince for all naturall endowments as this day breaths in Europe or for a long time has ſwayed a Scepter in Britaine) yet while ſuch unlucky birds neſt in his Cabin and men ſo ungraciouſly principled doe daily beſiege him, what can his good people doe but ſit downe with mournfull eyes and bleeding hearts, till the Lord amend theſe otherwiſe remediles and inſuperable evills? but I hold heer leaſt I tranſgreſſe to farr the bounds of an Epiſtle?</p>
            <p>I account it an advantage to have your Lordſhip my judge in what heere and in my following treatiſe,
<note place="margin">The reaſon of the dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> I ſpake of Religion, the liberties of our country and the Royall Family: I know non fitter then your Lordship, both to diſcerne and decerne in all theſe matters. Me thinks I may ſay it without flattery (which I never much loved either in my ſelfe or others) that among all our Nobles for conſtancy in a zealous profeſſion, for exemplary practiſe in publick and privat duties; the mercy of God has given to your Lordship a reputation ſecond to none. And for a rigid adhaerence to the Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of your Country, according to that auncient diſpoſition of your moſt Noble Family, noted in our Hiſtorians, eſpecially that Prince of them <hi>Georg Buchanan,</hi> the Tutor of your <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> I know none in our Land who wil pretend to goe before you, and for the affairs of the King, your intereſt of blood in the Royall Family is ſo well known, that it would be a ſtrange im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency in me, if in your audience I durſt be bold wittingly to give ſiniſtrous information. Praying to God that what in the candid ingenuity &amp; true zeale of my ſpirit, I preſent under your Lordſhips patrociny unto the eye of the World, for the vindication of my mother Church and Country, from the Sicophantick accuſations of a Stigmatiſed incendiary may produce the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded effects,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I reſt your <hi>Lordships in all Chriſtian duety, R. B. G.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hague</hi> 
                  <date> this 28 <hi>May</hi> / 7 <hi>Iunie.</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52046:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The praelaticall faction continue reſolute, that the King and all his people shall perish, rather then the praelats, be not reſtored to their former places of power, for to ſet up Popery, Profani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Tirranny, in all the three Kingdomes.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hile the Comiſſioners of the Church and Kingdome of Scotland,
<note place="margin">The unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonablenes of Doctor Brambles warning.</note> were on their way to make their firſt addreſſes to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, for to condole his moſt lamentable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and to make offer of their beſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and ſervices for his comfort, in this time of his great diſtreſſe; it was the wiſedome and charity of the praelaticall party, to ſend out <hi>Doctor Bramble,</hi> to meet them with his Faire Warning. For what elſe? but to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in the very entry from tendering their propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and before ever they were heard, to ſtop his Majeſties eares with grievous praejudice, againſt all that poſſibly they could ſpeake; though the world ſees that the only apparent fountaine of hope upon earth, for recovery of the wofully confounded affaires of the King, is in the hands of that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praelaticall nation: but it is the hope of theſe who love the welfaire of the King and his people, of the Churches and Kingdomes of Britain, that the hand of God, which hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all the former devices of the Praelats, shall crush this their engine alſo.
<note place="margin">The irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional way of the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our warner undertaketh to oppugne the Scotes diſcipline in a way of his owne, none of the moſt rational. He does not
<pb facs="tcp:52046:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52046:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52046:7"/>ſo much as pretend to ſtate a queſtion, nor in his whole book to bring againſt any maine poſition of his oppoſites, either Scripture, father or reaſon, nor ſo much as aſſay to anſwer any one of their arguments againſt Epiſcopacy; onely hee culs out ſome of their by-tenets, belonging little or nothing to the maine queſtions, and from them takes occaſion to gather together in a heape all the calumnies which of old, or of late their knowne enemies out of the forge of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and fraud, did obtrude on the credulity of ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: alſo ſome detorted paſſages from the bookes of their friends, to bring the way of that Church in deteſtation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any juſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe practiſes in our warner,
<note place="margin">The moſt of his ſtuffe is borrowed and long agoe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</note> are the leſs pardonable, that though he knowes the chiefe of his allegations, to bee but borrowed from his late much beloved Comerads Maſter Corbet in his <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor, and Maſter Maxewell</hi> in his <hi>Iſſachars Burden,</hi> yet he was neither deterred by the ſtrange punishments, which God from heaven inflicted vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly on both theſe calumniatores of their mother Church, nor was pleaſed in his repeating of their calumnious argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to releeve any of them from the exceptions under the which they ſtand publickly confuted, I ſuppoſe to his own diſtinct knowledge, I know certainly, to the open view of thouſands in Scotland, England and Ireland; but it makes for the warners deſigne to diſſemble here in Holland, that ever he heard of ſuch books as <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor, and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſachars Burden,</hi> much leſſe of <hi>Maſter Baylies anſwer</hi> to both, printed ſome yeares agoe at London, Edinburgh and Amſterdam, without a rejoinder from any of that faction to this day.
<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious bitternes of the warners ſpirit.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How ever let our warner be heard. In the very firſt page of his firſt chapter, wee may taſt the ſweetnes of his meek Spirit: at the verie entrie, he concludeth but without any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52046:7"/>pretence to an argument there or elſe where, <hi>the diſcipline of the Church of Scotland to be their owne invention, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they dote, the Diana, which themſelves have canonized, their own dreams, the counterfeyt image which they faine hath fallen down from Iupiter, which they ſo much adore, the very quinteſſence of refined popery, not only moſt injurious to the civill Magiſtrat, moſt oppreſſive to the ſubject, moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to both; but alſo inconſiſtent with all formes of civill governement, deſtructive to all ſorts of Policy, a rack to the conſcience, the heavieſt preſſure that can fall on a people.</hi> So much truth and ſobernes doth the warner breath out in his very firſt page.</p>
            <p>Though he had no regard at all to the cleare paſſages of Holy Scripture, whereupon the Scotes doe build their Anti-Epiſcopall tenets; nor any reverence to the harmony of the reformed Churches, which unanimouſly joyne with the Scotes in the maine of their diſcipline, eſpecially in that which the Doctor hates moſt therein, the rejection of Fpiſcopacy: yet me thinks ſome little reſpect might have appeared in the man to the authority of the Magiſtrat, and civil Lawes, which are much more ingeminated by this worthy divine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all his book, then the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Can hee ſo ſoon forget that the whole diſcipline of the Church of Scotland, as it is there taught and practiſed,
<note place="margin">The war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtricks at the Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline through the Kings ſides.</note> is eſtablished by acts of Parliament, and hath all the ſtrength which the King and State can give to a civil Law? the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may wel be grieved, but hardly can he be ignorant, that the Kings Majeſtie this day does not at all queſtion the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of theſe ſanctions: what ever therefore be the Doctors thoughts, yet ſo long as hee pretends to keep upon his face the maſke of loyalty, he muſt be content to eat his former words, yea, to burne his whole book: otherwiſe hee layes, againſt his own profeſſions, a ſlander upon the King, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52046:8"/>His Royal Father, of great ignorance, or huge unjuſtice, the one having eſtablished, the other offring to eſtablish by their civill lawes, a Church diſcipline for the whole nation of Scotland, which truly is the quinteſſence of Popery, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and deſtructive to all formes of civill governement, and the heavieſt preſſure that can fall on a people.</p>
            <p>All the cauſe of this choler which the warner is pleaſed to ſpeake out;
<note place="margin">In the threshold hee ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles on the Kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> is the attempt of the Scotes, to obtrude their diſcipline upon the King, contrary to the dictars of his own conſcience, and to compell forraigne Churches to embrace the ſame. Anſ. Is it not preſumption in our warner, ſo ſoone to tell the world in print what are the dictats of the Kings conſcience, as yet he is not his Majeſties confeſſor, and if the Clerk of the Cloſet had whiſpered ſome what in his eare, what he heard in ſecret, hee ought not to have proclaimed it without a warrant; but we doe altogether miſtruſt his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of the Kings conſcience: for who will beleeve him, that a knowing and a juſt King will ever be content, to command and impoſe on a whole Nation by his Lawes, a diſcipline contrary to the dictats of his owne conſcience. This great ſtumble upon the Kings conſcience in the firſt page, muſt be an ominous ceſpitation on the threshold.</p>
            <p>The other imputation had no juſt ground:
<note place="margin">The Scots never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to impoſe any thing upon En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</note> the Scotes did never medle, to impoſe any thing upon forraigne Churches, there is queſtion of none, but the English; and the Scotes were never ſo preſumptuous, as to impoſe any thing of theirs upon that Church. It was the aſſembly of divines at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, convocat by the King and Parliament of England, which after long deliberation, and much debate, unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly concluded the Preſbiterian diſcipline in all the parts thereof, to be agreable to the word of God: it was the two Houſes of the Parliament of England without a contrary voice, who did ordaine the abolition of Epiſcopacy, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52046:8"/>the ſetting up of Presbyteryes and Synods in England and Ireland. Can heere the Scotes be ſaid to compell the English to dance after their pype, when their own aſſembly of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines begins the ſong, when the Lords and Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in the Parliament of England concurre without a diſcording opinion, when the King himſelfe for perfecting the harmony offers, to adde his voice for three whole yeares together?</p>
            <p>In the remainder of the chapter the warner layes upon the Scotes three other crimes: firſt,
<note place="margin">The elder praelats of England were E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtians, and more, but the younger are as much anti-Eraſtian as the moſt riged of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</note> That they count it Eraſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme to put the governement of the Church in the hand of the Magiſtrat. Anſw. The Doctors knowledge is greater then to bee ignorant, that all theſe goe under the name of Eraſtians, who walking in Eraſtus ways of flattering the Magiſtrat, to the prejudice of the juſt rights of the Church, run yet out much beyond Eraſtus perſonall tenets; I doubt if that man went ſo far as the Doctor heere and elſe where, to make all Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, but a part of the Magiſtrats civill power, which for its execution, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Governours of any ſtate may derive out of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of their ſupremacy to what ever hands civill or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick themſelfes think fit to commit it. Let the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor adde to this much knowledge, but a little ingenuity, and he shall confes that his Brethren the Later Bishops, who claime Epiſcopacy by divine right, are all as much againſt this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtian Caeſaro-papiſme, as any Preſbiterian in Scotland. The elder Bishops indeed of England and all the Lawes there for Epiſcopacy ſeeme to be point blank according to the Eraſtian errours: for they make the crowne and royall ſupremacy the originall, root and fountaine whence all the diſcipline of the Church doth flow: as before the days of Henry the eight it did out of the Popes head-ship of the Church under Chriſt. How ever let the Doctor ingenuouſly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52046:9"/>ſpeake out his ſence, and I am deceived, if he shall not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that how groſſe an Eraſtian ſo ever himſelfe and the elder Bishops of England might have been, yet that long agoe, the moſt of his praelatical friends have become as much oppoſit to Eraſtianiſme, as the moſt rigid of the Presbiterians.</p>
            <p>The other crime he layes to the charge of the Scotes is,
<note place="margin">The Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes firſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt crime is irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliablenes with Rome.</note> that they admit no latitude in Religion, but will have every opinion afundamentall article of faith, and are averſe from the reconciliation of the Proteſtant Churches: Anſ. If the warner had found it ſeaſonable to vent a little more of his true ſence in this point, he had charged this great crime far more home upon the heade of the Scotes: for indeed though they were ever far from denying the true degrees of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which doe cleerly appeare among the multitude of Chriſtian truthes, yet the great quarrell heer of the warner and his freinds againſt them, is that they ſpoiled the Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burian deſigne of reconcealing the Proteſtant Churches not among themſelfes, but with the Church of Rome. When theſe good men were with all earneſtnes proclaming the greateſt controverſies of Papiſts and Proteſtants, to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no fundamentalls but only diſputable opinions, wherein beleefe on either ſide was ſafe enough, and when they found that the Papiſts did ſtand punctually to the Tenets of the Church of Rome, and were obſtinately unwilling to come over to England, their great labour was that the English and the reſt of the Proteſtants, caſting aſide their needleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of problematick truths, in piety, charity and zeale, to make up the breach and take away the shiſme, should be at all the paines to make the journey to Rome. While this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne is far advanced and furiouſly driven on in all the three Kingdomes, and by none more in Yreland then the Bishop of Derry, behold the rude and plaine blewcapes ſtep in to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52046:9"/>the play and marre all the game: by no arte, by no terrour can theſe be gotten alongs to ſuch a reconciliation. This was the firſt and greateſt crime of the Scotes, which the Doctor here glances at, but is ſo wyſe and modeſt a man as not to bring it above board.</p>
            <p>The laſt charge of the chapter is,
<note place="margin">The Scotes were ever anti epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall.</note> that the Scotes keep not ſtill that reſpect to the Bishops of England, which they were wont of old in the beginning of Queen Elizabeths reigne. Anſ. In that letter cited by the warner from the generall aſſembly of Scotland. 1566. Seſſ. 3. there is no word of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation to the office of Epiſcopacy: they ſpeake to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of England in no other quality or relation, but as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word, the higheſt ſtile they give them is, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Paſtors and Brethren; the tenour of the whole Epiſtle is a grave and brotherly admonition to beware of that fatall concomitant of the moſt moderat Epiſcopacy, the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the beſt and moſt zealous ſervants of Chriſt for idle &amp; fruitles Ceremonies. How great a reverence the Church of Scotland at that time carried to praelacy, may be ſeen in their ſupplication to the ſecret counſell of Scotland, in that ſame aſſembly the very day and Seſſion wherein they write the letter in hand to the Bishops of England. The Arch-Bishop of S. Andrews being then uſurping juriſdiction over the miniſtry by ſome warrant from the ſtate, the Aſſembly was grieved, not only with the popery of that Bishop, but with his <hi>auncient juriſdiction,</hi> which in all Bishops, Popish and proteſtant, is one and the ſame: That juriſdiction was the only matter of their preſent complaint; and in relation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they aſſure the counſel in diſtinct tearmes, that <hi>they would never be more ſubject unto that uſurped tiranny the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would be to the devill himſelfe:</hi> So reverend an opinion had the Church of Scotland at that time of Epiſcopall juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>But ſuppone that ſome fourſcore yeares agoe, the Scotes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52046:10"/>before they had taſted the fruits of Proteſtant Bishops,
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates lately were found in the act of intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, and Tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny into the Kingdom.</note> had judged them tolerable in England, yet ſince that time by the long tract of miſchiefes, which conſtantly has accompanied the order of praelacy, they have been put upon a more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curat inſpection of its nature, and have found it not only a needles, but a noxious and poyſonous weed, neceſſare to be plucked up by the root, and caſt over the hedge. Beſide al its former malefices, it hath been deprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of late in the very act of everting the foundations, both of Religion and governement, of bringing in Popery and Tiranny, in the Churches and States of all the three Kingdomes, (<hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burian ſelf conviction cap.</hi> 1.)</p>
            <p>And for theſe crimes, it was condemned, killed, and buried in Scotland, by the unanimous conſent of King, Church and Kingdom: when England thereafter both in their Aſſembly and Parliament, without a diſcording voice had found it neceſſary, to root out that unhappy plant, as long agoe with great wiſedome, it had been caſt out of all the reſt of the reformed Churches, had not the Scotes all the reaſon in the World, to applaud ſuch pious juſt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary reſolutions of their English Brethren, though the warner should call it the greateſt crime?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trover ſie in Scotland betwixt the King and the Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods.</note> 
                  <hi>The Preſbiterians aſſert poſitively, the Magiſtrats right to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat Synods, to confirme their acts, to reforme the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches within their dominions.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the ſecond Chapter the warner charges the Scotes preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, with the overthrowing the Magiſtrats right in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52046:10"/>convocating of Synods. When he comes to prove this, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets his challenge: and digreſſes from it to the Magiſtrates power of choyſing elders and making Eccleſiaſtick lawes, avowing that theſe things are done in Scotland by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick perſons alone, without conſent of the king or his counſel. Anſ. It ſeemes our Warner is very ignorant of the way of the Scotes diſcipline, the ordinary and ſet meetings of all aſſemblies both nationall and provincionall ſince the firſt reformation are determined by acts of Parliament, with the Kings conſent, ſo betwixt the King and the Church of Scotland, there is no queſtion for the convocating of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary aſſemblies, for extraordinary, no man in Scotland did ever controvert the Kings power to call them when and where he pleaſed: as for the inhaerent power of the Church to meet for diſcipline, alſwell as for worship, the Warner fals on it heereafter, we muſt therefore paſſe it in this place.</p>
            <p>What hee meanes to ſpeake of the Kings power in choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing elders or making Eccleſiaſtick Lawes, himſelfe knowes:
<note place="margin">The war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian and Tirannick principles, hated by the King.</note> his Majeſtie in Scotland did never require any ſuch privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as the election of elders, or Commiſſioners to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or members of any incorporation, civill or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick, where the Lawes did not expreſly provide the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to be in the crowne. The making of Eccleſiaſtick Lawes in England, alſwell as in Scotland, was ever with the Kings good contentment, referred to Eccleſiaſtick aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies: but the Warner ſeemes to be in the mind of theſe his companions, who put the power of preaching, of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacraments and diſcipline in the ſupreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat alone, and derives it out of him as the head of the Church to what members he thinks expedient to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicat it: alſo that the legiſlative power alſwell in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick as civill affairs, is the property of the King alone. That the Parliaments and generall aſſemblies are but his arbitrary
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52046:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52046:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52046:12"/>counſels, the one for matters of the ſtate, the other for matters of the Church, with whom or without whom hee makes acts of Parliament and Church cannons, according to his good pleaſure, that all the offices of the Kingdome, both of Church and State are from him, as he gives a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to whom he will to be a sheriffe or juſtice of peace, ſo he ſends out whom he pleaſeth to preach &amp; celebrate Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments by virtue of his regal miſſion. The Warner and his Eraſtian friends may well extend the royall ſupremacy to this largenes, but no King of Scotland was ever willing to accept of ſuch a power though by erroneous flaterers, ſometimes obtruded upon him, <hi>(ſee Canterburian ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. cap. ult.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Warner will not leave this matter in generall,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Scotes procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</note> he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends to inſtance a number of particular incroatchments of the Scots Presbiters upon the royall authority: wee muſt diſpence in all his diſcourſe with a ſmall peckadillo in reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, hee muſt bee permitted to lay all the faults of the Presbiterians in Scotland upon the back of the Preſbitery it ſelfe, as if the faylings of officers were naturall to, and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable from their office: mis-kenning this little mote of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequentiall argumenting, we will goe through his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular charges, the firſt is, that King James anno 1579, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the generall aſſembly, to make no alteration in the Church-Policy, till the next Parliament, but they contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Kings command, determined poſitively all their diſcipline without delay, and queſtioned the Arch-Biſchop of Sainct Andrews for voting in Parliament according to the undoubted Lawes of the Land, yea twenty Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters did hold the generall aſſembly at Aberdeen after it was diſcharged by the King. Anſ. The Warner poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly may know, yet certainly he doth not care what he writes in theſe things to which hee is a meere ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52046:12"/>the authentick regiſters of the Church of Scotland convinces him heire of falshood.
<note place="margin">Bishops were abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and Presby te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſet up in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land with King Iames conſent.</note> His Majeſtie did write from Stirling to the generall aſſembly at Edinburgh 1579, that they should ceaſſe from concluding any thing in the diſcipline of the Church, during the time of his minority; upon this deſire the aſſembly did abſtaine from all concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, only they named a committee to goe to Striveling for conference which his Majeſtie upon that ſubject. What followeth thereupon? I. Immediatly a Parliament is called in October 1579, and in the firſt act declares and grantes juriſdiction unto the Kirk, whilk conſiſtes in the true preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word of Jeſus Chriſt, correction of manners, and adminiſtration of the true Sacraments, and declares that there is no other face of Kirk, nor other face of Religion then is preſently by the favour of God eſtablished within this realme, and that there be no other juriſdiction Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal acknowledged within this realme then that whilk is, and shalbe within the ſamen Kirk, or that which flowes therfra, concerning the premiſſes. II. In Aprile 1580. Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made <hi>ex deliberatione Dominorum Conſilii</hi> in name of the King, charging all Superintendentes and Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Miniſters ſerving at Kirkes. To note the names of all the ſubjectes alſweel men as women ſuſpected to be Papiſtes or — and to admonish them — to give Confeſſion of their faith according to the Forme approved by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and to ſubmitte unto the diſcipline of the true Kirk within a reaſonable ſpace —: and if they faile — that the Superintendents or Commiſſioners preſente a role or catalogue of their names unto the King and Lords of Secret Counſell whereby they shalbe for the time, between and the 15 day of Iulie nixt to come, to the end that the actes of Parliament made againſt ſuch perſones may be execute. III. The shorte Confeſſion wes drawen up at the Kings
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52046:13"/>command, which was firſt ſubſcrived by his royall hand, and an act of Secret Counſell commanding all ſubjectes to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrive the ſame; as is to be ſeen by the Act printed with the Confeſſion, wherein Hierarchie is abjured, that is (as hath been ſince declared by Nationall aſſemblies and Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes both called and held by the King) epiſcopacie is abjured. IV. In the aſſemblies 1580 and 1581 that Confeſſion of faith and the ſecond book of diſcipline (after debating many praeceding years) were approved (except one chapter <hi>de dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conatu</hi>) by the Aſſemblie, the Kings Commiſſioner being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preſente, not finde we any thing oppoſed then by him: yea then at his Majeſties ſpeciall direction about fifty claſſical Presbyteries were ſet up over all Scotland which remaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day, Was there heer any contempt of the roy all authority?</p>
            <p>About that time ſome noble men had gote the revenues of the Biſſhop-rickes for their private uſe; and becauſe they could not enjoy them by any legal right, therefore for elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Law, they did effectuate that ſome Miniſters should have the title of this or that Bishopricke; and the revenues were gathered in the name of this titulare or tulchan Bishop, albeit hee had but little part: e. g. Robert Montgomerie Miniſter at Sterline was called Arch-Bishop of Glaſgow: and ſo it can bee inſtanced in other Bishop-rickes and abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Now this kind of praelats pretended no right to any part of the Epiſcopall office, either in ordination or juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: when ſome of theſe men began to creep in to vote for the Church in Parliament, without any Law of the State, without any commiſſion from the Church, the generall aſſembly diſcharged them, being Miniſters, to practiſe any more ſuch illegall inſolencies, with this ordinance of the Church, after a little debate, King James at that time did shew his good ſatisfaction.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52046:13"/>
            <p> But the Warner heere jumps over noleſſe then twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years time from the aſſembly at Edinburgh 1579,
<note place="margin">The inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of the much maligned aſſembly of Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen.</note> to that at Aberdeen 1605, then was King James by the English Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops perſwaſion reſolved to put down the generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Scotland, contrary to the Lawes and conſtant prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of that Church, from the firſt reformation to that day. The act of Parliament did bear that once at leaſt a yeare the aſſembly should meet, and after their buſines was ended they should name time &amp; place for the next aſſembly. When they had met in the yeare 1602, they were moved to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe without doing any thing for two whole yeares to 1604, when then they were conveened at the time and place agreed to by his Majeſtie, they were content upon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties deſire without doing any thing againe to adjourne to the nixt yeare 1605, at Aberdeen, when that dyet came his Majeſties Commiſſioner offered them a Letter: To the end they might be an Aſſembly and ſo in a Capacity to receave his Majeſties Letter, with the Commiſſioners good pleaſure they ſate downe, they named their Moderator and Clark they received and read the Kings letter commanding them to riſe, which they obeyed without any farther action at all but naming a dyet for the nixt meeting according to the Lawes and conſtant practiſe of Scotland, hereupon by the pernicious counſel of Arch-Bishop Banckroft at London, the King was ſtirred up to bring ſore trouble upon a number of gracious Miniſters.
<note place="margin">Chriſtmas and other ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in Scotland, both by Church and State.</note> This is the whole matter which to the Warner heir is ſo tragick an inſolence, that never any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament durſt attempt the like. See more of this in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall vindication.</p>
            <p>The nixt inſtance of our Presbiteryes uſurpation upon the Magiſtrat is their abolition, (before any ſtatute of Parliament thereupon) of the Church feſtivals in their firſt book of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Anſ. Conſider the grievouſneſſe of this crime, in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52046:14"/>the intervall of Parliaments, the great counſel of Scotland in the minority of the Prince entruſted by Parliament to rule the Kingdome, did charge the Church to give them in wryte their judgement about matters Eccleſiaſticall: in obedience to this charge the Church did preſent the counſel with a wryte named ſince the firſt book of diſciplin: which the Lords of counſel did approve, ſubſcribe and ratify by an Act of State: a part of the firſt head in that wryte was that Chriſtmas, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphany, purification, and other fond feaſts of the virgin Mary, as not warranted by the holy Scriptures, should bee laid aſide. Was it any encroachment upon the Magiſtrate for the Church to give this advice to the privy counſell when earneſtly they did crave it? the people of Scotland ever ſince have shewed their ready obedience to that direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church founded upon Scripture, and backed from the beginning with an injunction of the ſtate.</p>
            <p>His third inſtance of the Church of Scotlands uſurpation upon the Magiſtrat is,
<note place="margin">The friends of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy thryves not in Scotland.</note> their abolition of Epiſcopacy in the aſſembly 1580, when the Law made it treaſon to impugne the authority of Bishops, being the third eſtate of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Anſ. The Warner ſeemes to have no more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the affairs of Scotland, then of Japan or Utopia, the Law hee ſpeakes of was not in being ſome yeares after 1580, how ever all the generall aſſemblyes of Scotland are authoriſed by act of Parliament, to determine finally with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an appeale in all Eccleſiaſtick affaires: in the named aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly Lundie the Kings Commiſſioner did ſit and conſent in his Majeſties name to that act of abolition, as in the nixt aſſembly 1581, the Kings Commiſſioner Caprinton did erect in his Majeſties name the Presbiteryes in all the Land; it is true, three yeares thereafter a wicked Courtier Captaine James Stuart, in a shadow of a cloſſe and not ſummoned Parliament, did procure an act to abolish Presbiteries and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52046:14"/>erect Bishops, but for this and all the reſt of his crimes that evill man was quickly rewarded by God before the world, in a terrible deſtruction: theſe acts of his Parliament the very nixt yeare were diſclaimed by the King, the Bishops were put downe, and the Presbitry was ſet up again, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more removed to this day.</p>
            <p>The Warners digreſſion to the perpetuity of Bishops in Scotland, to the acts of the Church and State for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, is but to shew his ignorance in the Scotes ſtory: what ever be the Epiſcopall boaſtings of other Nations, yet it is evident that from the firſt entrance of Chriſtian Religion into Scotland, Preſbiters alone without Bishops for ſome hundred yeares did governe that Church: and after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation their was no Bishop in that Land, but in tittle and benefice till the yeare 1610; when Bancroft did conſecrat three Scotes Miniſters, all of them men of evill report, whom that violent Commiſſioner the Earle of Dunbar in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and null aſſembly of Glaſgow, got authoriſed in ſome pairt of a Bishops office; which part only and no more was ratified in a poſterior Parliament. Superintendents are no where the ſame with Bishops much leſſe in Scotland where for a time only till the Churches were planted, they were uſed as ambulatory Commiſſioners, and viſitors to preach the word, and adminiſter the Sacraments for the ſupply of vacant and unſetled congregations.</p>
            <p>The fourth inſtance is the Churches obtruding the ſecond book of diſcipline, without the ratification of the State. Anſ.
<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book of diſciplin why not al ratified in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> For the Eccleſiaſtick enjoining of a generall aſſemblyes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees a particular ratification of Parliament is unneceſſary; generall acts of Parliament commanding obedience to the acts of the Church, are a ſufficient warrant from the State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, that ſecond book of diſciplin was much debated with the King, and at laſt in the generall aſſembly 1590, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52046:15"/>was obtained unto it: for in that aſſembly where unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly the ſubſcription of the ſecond book of diſciplin by all the miniſters of the Kingdome was decried, his Majeſtie ſome time in perſon and alwayes by the chancelor his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner was preſent, and in the act for ſubſcription Seſſ. 10. Auguſti 8. it is expreſly ſaid that not only all the Miniſters but alſo all the Commiſſioners praeſent did conſent, among which Commisſioners the chancelor, his Majeſties Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner was chief. But neither the King nor the Church could get it to paſſe the Parliament in regaird of the oppoſition, which ſome States-men did make unto theſe parts thereof, which touched on their owne intereſt of unjuſt advantage, this was the only ſtick.</p>
            <p>The next inſtance of the Churches encroachement is their uſurpation of all the old rents of the clergy,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that a crime, which himſelfe counts a virtue.</note> as the Churches patrimony, and their decerning in anaſſembly that nothing in the nixt Parliament should paſſe before the Church were fully reſtored to her rents. Anſ. Conſider heere the Warners hypocriſie and unjuſtice, he challenges the Preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians for that which no praelate in the world did ever eſteem a fault, a meer declaration of their judgement that the Church had a juſt right to ſuch rents, as by law and long poſſesſion were theirs, and not taken away from them by any lawfull meanes. What if heere they had gone on with the moſt of the praelaticall party to advance that right to a <hi>jus divinum?</hi> what if they had put themſelves by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Court, into the poſſesſion of that right, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a proceſſe, as diverſe of the Warners friends were begun lately to doe in all the three Kingdomes? but all that he can here challenge the Scotes for, is a meere declaration of their ſimple right, with a ſupplication to the Regent his grace, that hee would indeavour in the nixt Parliament, to procure a ninth part of the Churches patrimony, for the mantainance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52046:15"/>of the miniſtry, and the poore of the country: for all the rent that the Churches then could obtaine or did petition, was but a third of the thirds of the benefices or tithes. That ever any aſſembly in Scotland did make any other addreſſe to the Parliament for ſtipends then by way of humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it is a great untruth.</p>
            <p>The laſt inſtance is, the erecting of Presbyteries through al the Kingdome, by an act of the Church alone. Anſ. I have showne already the untruth of this alleadgeance; the proofe heere brought for it, is grounded only upon an ambiguous word which the Warners ignorance in the Scotish diſciplin and Presbitery (though the maine ſubject of his booke) permits him not to underſtand. The Presbyteries were ſet up by the King after the aſſembly 1580, but the ſecond booke of diſcipline of which alone the citation ſpeaks, how ever enjoind by many aſſemblies, yet it could never be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ratified in any Parliament, only becauſe of theſe parts of it which did ſpeake for the patrimony of the Church, and oppugne the right of patronages.</p>
            <p>How well the Warner hath proven the Presbiterian prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes to be injurious to the Magiſtrate we have conſidered,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a groſſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtian.</note> poſſibly he will bee more happy in his nixt undertaking, in his demonſtrations that their doctrinall principles doe tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on the Magiſtrats ſupremacy and Lawes; their firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple hee takes out of the ſecond book of diſciplin. Cap. 7. That no Magiſtrat nor any but Eccleſiaſtick perſons may vote in Synods. Anſ. Though I find nothing of this in the place cited, yet there is nothing in it that croſſeth either the Laws or the Kings ſupremacy: for according to the acts of Parliament of Scotland both old and late and the conſtant practiſe of that Church, the only members of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries are Miniſters and ruling elders. Is it the Warners minde to vent here his ſuper-Eraſtianiſme, that all Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52046:16"/>aſſemblies Claſſicall, Provinciall, nationall are but the arbitrary Courts of the Magiſtrat for to adviſe him in the execution of his inhaerent power about matters Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall; and for this cauſe, that it is in his arbitrement to give a deciſive voyce in all Church aſſemblies, to whom and how many ſo ever hee will? Though this may bee the Warners minde, as it hath been ſome of his friends, yet the moſt of the praelaticall party will not man taine him heerein. How ever, ſuch principles are contrary to the Lawes of Scotland, to the profeſſions alſo and practiſes of all the Princes and Magiſtrats that ever have lived there.</p>
            <p>But the Warner heere may poſſibly glaunce at another principle of his good friends,
<note place="margin">Praelatical principles impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate alſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid peace, betwixt the King and his Kingdoms</note> who have been willing lately to vent before al Britaine in print their Elevating the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of Soveraignes ſo far above Lawes, that what ever peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have obtained to bee eſtabliſhed by never ſo many aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and Parliaments and confirmed with never ſo many great ſeales of ratification, and peaceably injoyed by never ſo long a poſſeſſion, yet it is nothing but commendable wiſedome and juſtice for the ſame Prince who made the firſt conceſſions or any of his ſucceſſors when ever they find themſelfes ſtrong enough, to cancell all and make void what ever Parliaments, Aſſemblies, royall ratifications, and the longeſt poſſeſſion made foolish people beleeve to be moſt firme and unqueſtionable. To this purpoſe Bishop Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel (from whom much of this warning is borrowed) doth ſpeak in his <hi>Sacro-Sancta regum Majeſtas.</hi> Though this had been the Cabine divinity of our praelats, yet what can be their intentions in ſpeaking of it out in theſe times of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, themſelves muſt declare: for the cleare conſequente of ſuch doctrine ſeemes to be a neceſſity either of ſuch Warners perpetuall banishment from the Courts and eares of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, or elſe that ſubjects be kept up for ever in a ſtrong
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52046:16"/>jealouſy, and feare that they can never be ſecure of their liberties, though never ſo well ratified by Lawes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Princes any longer then the ſword and power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in their owne hand to preſerve what they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Such Warners ſo long as they are poſſeſſed with ſuch maximes of ſtate, are cleare everters of the firſt funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of truſt betwixt Soveraignes and ſubjects, they take away all poſſibility of any ſolid peace of any confident ſetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any troubled ſtate, before both parties be totally ruined or one become ſo ſtrong that they need no more to feare the others malcontentment in any time to come.</p>
            <p>Our ſecond challenged principle is that wee teach the whole power of convocating aſſemblies to be in the Church.
<note place="margin">Eraſtian praelats evert the legall foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Anſ. The Warners citations prove not that we maintaine any ſuch aſſertion, our doctrin and conſtant practiſe hath been to aſcribe to the King a power of calling Synods, when and whereſoever he thought fit, but that which the Warner ſeemes to point at is, our tenet of an intrinſicall power in the Church to meet, as for the word and Sacraments ſo for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplin; in this all who are Chriſtians, old and late, the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall and Popiſh party as well as others, goe along with us to mantaine in doctrine and practiſe, a neceſſity even in times of perſecution, that the Church muſt meet for the worship of God and execution of Eccleſiaſtick diſciplin among their owne members. In this the doctrine and practiſe of the Scots is according to their ſetled lawes, uncontroverted by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie. If the Warner will mantaine, that in reaſon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience al the Churches of the world are oblidged to diſſolve and never more to meet when an erroneous Magiſtrat by his Tyrannous edict commands them to doe ſo, let him call up Eraſtus from the dead to be diſciplined in this new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the praelats impious loyalty.</p>
            <p>The third principle is that the judgment of true and falſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52046:17"/>doctrine of ſuſpenſion and deprivation of Miniſters belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Church.
<note place="margin">The finall determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick cauſes by the Lawes of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</note> Anſ. If this be a great hereſie it is to be charged as much upon the ſtate as upon the Church, for the acts of Parliament give all this power to the Church, neith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er did the lawes of England or of any Chriſtian ſtate, popish or proteſtant, refuſe to the Church the determination of ſuch Eccleſiaſtick cauſes; ſome indeed doe debate upon the power of appeales from the Church, but in Scotland by the law, as no appeale in things civill goes higher then the Parliament ſo in matters Eccleſiaſtick none goes above the generall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. Complaints indeed may goe to the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for redreſſe of any wrong has been done in Eccleſiaſtick Courts, who being <hi>cuſtodes religionis</hi> may by their coercive power command Eccleſiaſtick Courts to rectifie any wrong done by them contraire to Scripture, or if they perſiſt take order with them. But that two or three praelats should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Court of delegats, to receave appeales from a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſembly, neither Law nor practiſe in Scotland did ever admit, nor can the word of God or any Equity require it. In the Scotes aſſemblies no cauſes are agitat but ſuch as the Parliament hath agreed to bee Eccleſiaſtick and of the Churches cogniſance: no Proceſſe about any Church rent was ever cognoſced upon in Scotland but in a civill Court: its very falſe that ever any Church cenſure, much leſſe the higheſt of excommunication did fall upon any for robbing the Church of its patrimony.
<note place="margin">The divine right of diſcipline, is the tenet of the moſt of praelats.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our fourth challenged principle is that wee maintain Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick juriſdiction by a divine right. Anſ. Is this a huge crime? is there divine in the world, either Papiſt or Poteſtant, except a few praelaticall Eraſtians, but they doe ſo? If the Warner will profeſse (as it ſeemes hee muſt) the contradiction of that which he aſcribes to us, his avowed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net muſt bee that all Eccleſiaſtick power flowes from the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52046:17"/>Magiſtrat, that the Magiſtrat himſelf may execute all Church cenſures, that all the Officers appointed by Chriſt for the governement of his Church, may bee laid aſide, and ſuch a kind of governors bee put in their place, as the Magiſtrate shalbe pleaſed to appoint: that the ſpirituall ſword and Kei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of heaven belong to the Magiſtrate by vertue of his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, als wel as the temporall ſword and the Keies of his earthly Kingdome: our difference heere from the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner will not (I hope) be found the greateſt hereſie.</p>
            <p>Our laſt challenged principle is,
<note place="margin">All the power of the Church in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and with the Magiſtrats conſente.</note> that wee will have all our power againſt the Magiſtrat, that is, although hee diſſent. Anſ. It is an evill comentare that al muſt be againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, which is done againſt his conſent: but in Scotland their is no ſuch caſe: for all the juriſdiction which the church there does enjoy, they have it with the conſent of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat: all is ratified to them by ſuch acts of Parliament as his Majeſtie doth not at all controvert. Concerning that odious caſe the Warner intimats, whither in time of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when the Magiſtrat claſsheth with the Church, any Eccleſiaſtick diſciplin be then to be exerciſed; himſelfe can better anſwer it then we, who with the auncient Chriſtians doe think, that on all hazards (even of life) the church may not be diſſolved, but muſt meet in dens and caves and in the wildernes for the word and Sacraments and keeping it ſelfe pure by the divine ordinance of diſcipline.
<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats rather then to lay aſide their owne inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, will keepe the King and his people in miſery for ever.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Having cleered all the pernicious practiſes and all the wicked Doctrines, which the Warner layes upon us, I think it needles to inſiſt upon theſe defenſes which he in his aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant charity brings for us, but in his owne way, that he may with the greater advantage impugne them: only I touch one paſſage whereupon he make injurious exclamations: that which Mr. Gileſpie in his theoremes wryts; when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate abuſes his power unto Tyranny and makes havock
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52046:18"/>of all, it is lawfull to reſiſt him by ſome extraordinary wayes and meanes, which are not ordinarily to bee allowed: ſee the principles from which all our miſeryes and the loſſe of our gracious Maſter have flowed. Anſ. Wee muſt heere yeeld to the Warner the great equity and neceſſity that every doctrine of a Presbyter, should be charged on the Presbytery it ſelfe, and that any Presbyter teaching the lawfulneſſe of a Parliaments defenſive armes is tantamont to the Churches taking of armes againſt the king. Theſe ſmall unconſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wee muſt permit the Warner to ſwallow downe without any ſtick, however wee doe deny that the maxime in hand was the fountaine of any our miſeryes, or the cauſe at all of the loſſe of our late Soveraigne. Did ever his Majeſtie or any of his adviſed counſellers declare it ſimply unlawfull for a Parliament, to take armes for defence in ſome extraordinary caſes, however the unhappines of the Canterburian Prelats did put his Majeſtie on theſe courſes, which did begin and promote all our miſery, and to the very laſt theſe men were ſo wicked as to refuſe the louſing of theſe bands which their hands had tyed about his miſinformed conſcience, yea to this day they will not give their conſent, that his Majeſtie, who now is, should lay aſide Epiſcopacy, were it for the gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the peaceable poſſeſſion of all his three Kingdomes, but are urgers of him night and day to adhaere to their errours, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hazard of all the miſeries that may come on his perſon, on his family and all his people: yet few of them to this day durſt be ſo bold as to print with this Warner, the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a Parliaments armes againſt the Tyranny of a Prince in any imaginable caſe, how extraordinary ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52046:18"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lawes and cuſtomes of Scotland admitte of no appeal from the generall aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN this chapter the challenge is,
<note place="margin">Appeals in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land from a generall aſſembly were no leſſe irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall then illegall.</note> that there are no appeales from the generall Aſſembly to the King, as in England from the Bishops Courts to the King in Chauncery, where a Commiſſion uſes to be given to delegats, who diſcuſſe the appeales. Anſ. The warner conſiders not the difference of the Government of the Church of Scotland from that which was in England. what the Parliament is in the State, that the generall aſſembly is in the Church of Scotland: both are the higheſt courts in their owne kind. There is no appeale any where in moderat Monarchies to the Kings perſon, but to the King in certaine legall courts; as the Warner here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth the appeale from Bishops lyes not, to the King in his perſon, but to the King in his court of Chauncery. As no man in Scotland is permitted to appeale in a civil cauſe from the Lords of Seſſion; much leſſe from the Parliament; ſo no man in an Eccleſiaſtick cauſe is permitted by the verie civil Law of Scotland to appeale from the general aſſembly. According to the Scots order &amp; practiſe, the King in perſon or elſe by his high Commiſſioner ſits als uſually in the generall aſſembly, as in Parliament. But though it were not ſo, yet an appeale from a generall aſſembly to be diſcuſſed in a Court of delegats, were unbeſeeming and unreaſonable, the one Court conſiſting of above two hundred, all choſen men the beſt and moſt able of the Kingdome; the other but of two or three, often of very ſmall either abilities or integrity, who yet may be more fitt to decerne in an Eccleſiaſtick cauſe then a ſingle Bishop over his officiall, the ordinary truſted in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52046:19"/>all acts of juriſdiction for the whole dioces. But the Scots way of managing Eccleſiaſtick cauſes is a great deale more juſt, ſafe and Satisfactory to any rationall man then that old popish order of the English, where all the ſpirituall juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the whole dioces was in the hand of one merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary officiall without all reliefe from his ſentence, except by an appeale, as of old to the pope and his delegats, ſo therafter to the King, though never to be cognoſced-upon by himſelfe, but as it was of old by two or three delegats,
<note place="margin">The Churches juſt ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt Montgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery and Adamſon was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven by the King and the parties themſelfe.</note> the weakeſt of all courts, often for the quality and ever for the number of the judges.</p>
            <p>Two inſtances are brought by the Warner to prove the Church of Scotlands ſtopping of appeals from the generall Aſſembly to the King, the caſes of <hi>Montgomery</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damſon:</hi> if the cauſes and events of the named caſes had been wel knowne to the Warner, as he made this chapter diſproportionally short, ſo readily he might have deleted it al together. Both theſe men were infamous not only in their Miniſteriall charges but in their life &amp; converſation; both became ſo inſolent that contrary to the eſtablished order of the Church &amp; Kingdome, being ſuborned by wicked ſtateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who in that day of darknes had wel neer brought ruine both to King and country, would needs take upon them the office of Arch-Bishops. While the aſſembly was in proces with them for their manifold and high miſdeameanors, the King was moved by them and their evill patrons, to shew his high diſpleaſure againſt the aſſemblyes of the Church. they for his Majeſties ſatiſfaction ſent their Commiſſioners and had many conferences; whereby the pride and contempt of theſe prelats did ſo encreaſe, that at laſt they drew the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication upon their own heads: the King after ſome time did acknowledge the equity of the Church proceedings, and profeſſed his contentment their with:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52046:19"/>both theſe unhappy men were brought to a humble confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their crimes, and ſuch ſignes of repentance, that both after a renunciation of their titulare Bishopriks were read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the function of the miniſtry, which they had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Never any other before or after in Scotland did appeale from the generall aſſembly to the King: the late excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicat praelats in their declinatour againſt the aſſembly of Glaſgow, did not appeale as (I remember) to the King, but to another generall aſſembly to bee conſtitute, according to their own Popish and Tyrannical principles.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faulty Miniſters in Scotland are leſſe exempted from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, then any other men.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The pride of prelats lately, but never the Presbitery did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their civil faults.</note>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Warner in his fourth Chapter offers to prove, that the Scottish diſcipline doth exempt Miniſters from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment for any treaſon or ſedition they can act in their pulpits. Anſ. This challenge is like the reſt, very falſe. The rules of the Church diſcipline in Scotland obliges Churchmen to bee ſubject to punishment, not only for every fault for which any other man is lyable to cenſure, but ordaines them to bee punished for ſundrie things, which in other men are not at all queſtionable: and what ever is cenſurable in any, they appoint it to be much more ſo in a Miniſter. It is very untrue, that the pulpits in Scotland are Sanctuaries for any crime, much leſſe for the grievous crimes of ſedition and treaſon. Let the Warner remember, how short a time it is, ſince an Epiſcopall chayre or a canonicall coate did priviledge in England and Ireland from all cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52046:20"/>either of Church or State, great numbers, who were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly knowne to be guilty of the fouleſt crimes. Was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Warners companion Bishop Aderton challenged for his Sodomy, ſo long as their commune patrone of Canterbury did rule the court? did the warner never heare of a prelate very ſibb to Doctour Bramble, who to this day was never cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to any account for flagrant ſcandals of ſuch crimes as in Scotland are punishable by the gallows? the Warner doth not well to inſiſt upon the Scots Clergie exempting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from civill punishments: no where in the world are Churchmen more free of crimes deſerving civil cogniſance then in Scotland: and if the ears and eyes of the world may be truſted, the popish clergy this day in Italy and Spaine are not ſo challengeable, as the praelaticall divines in England and Ireland lately were for many groſſe misdemeanors.</p>
            <p>But why does the Warners anger run out ſo farre as to the preachers in Holland?
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Holland.</note> is it becauſe he knoweth the Church diſciplin in Holland to be really the ſame with that he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnes in the Scots, and that all the reformed Churches doe joyne cordially with Scotland in their rejection of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy? is this a ground for him to ſlander our Brethren of Holland? Is it charity for him a ſtranger to publish to the world in print that the miniſters in Holland are ſeditious oratours, and that they ſaucily controll the Magiſtrats in their pulpits? Their crime ſeemes to be, that for the love of Chriſt their maſter, they are zealous in their doctrin, to preſſe upon the Magiſtrat as well as upon the people the true prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of piety, the ſanctification of the ſabbath day, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of hereſy and shiſme, and repentance for the ſins of the time &amp; place wherein they live. This is a crime whereof few of the Warners friends were wont to be guilty of: their shamefull ſilence and flattery was one of the great cauſes of all the ſins and calamities that have wracked the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52046:20"/>the ſtreame of their ſermons while the enjoyed the pulpit, was to encourage to ſuperſtition and contempt of piety, to ſing aſleepe by their ungracious way all, that gave eare unto them. The man is impatien, t to ſee the Paſtors of Holland or any where, to walk in another path then his own, and for this cauſe would ſtirre up their Magiſtrats againſt them: as it was his and his Brethrens cuſtome to ſtirre up the Magiſtrats of Britan and Ireland to impriſon, banish, and heavily vex the moſt zealous ſervants of God, only for their oppoſition to the praelats profanity and errours. The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (I hope) has not yet forgotten, how Doctor <hi>Bramble</hi> and his neighbour <hi>Lefly</hi> of Down did caſt out of the Miniſtry, and made flee out of the Kingdome, men moſt eminent for zeale, piety and learning, who in a short time had done more good in the houſe of God, then all the Bishops that ever were in Ireland, I meane Maſter <hi>Blaire,</hi> Maſter <hi>Levingſton,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Cuningham,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>The Warner needed not to have marked as a ſingularity of Geneva, that there all the Eccleſiaſticks, <hi>quâ tales,</hi> are punishable by the Magiſtrats for civil crimes; for wee know none of the reformed Churches, who were ever following Rome in exeeming the Clergy from ſaecular juriſdiction, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were the Canterburian Praelats: who indeed did skarre the moſt of Magiſtrats from medeling with a canonical coat though defiled with drunckeneſſe, adultery, ſcolding, fighting, and other evils, which were too common of late to that order.</p>
            <p>But how does hee prove,
<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of King Iames, was Biſhop A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damſons lying libel.</note> that the Scots Miniſters exempt themſelves from civill juriſdiction? firſt (ſaith he) by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of King James 1584. Anſ. That declaration was not from King James, as himſelfe did teſtify the yeare thereafter under his hand, but from Maſter <hi>Patrike Adam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who did acknowledge it to bee his owne upon his death
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52046:21"/>bed, and profeſſed his repentance for the lyes and ſlaunders, wherewith againſt his conſcience hee had fraughted that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous libell.</p>
            <p>His ſecond proofe is from the ſecond booke of diſcipline Chapter II,
<note place="margin">Though alwayes in England yet never in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land had Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie any juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over Miniſters.</note> It is abſurd that Commiſſaries haveing no func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Church, should be judges to Miniſters to depoſe them from their charges. Anſ. Though in England the Commiſſary and officiall was the ordinary judge to depoſe and excommunicat all the Miniſters of the dioceſe, yet by the Lawes of Scotland no Commiſſaries had ever any juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over Miniſters. But though the officialls juriſdiction together with their Lords the Bishops were abolished, yet doth it follow from this, that no other juriſdiction remaineth whereby Miniſters might be punished either by Church and State, according to their demerits? is not this ſtrongly reaſoned by the Warner?</p>
            <p>His third proofe is the caſe of James Gibſon,
<note place="margin">Iames Gibſon was never abſolved by the Church from his Proces.</note> who had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in pulpit againſt the King, and was only ſuſpended, yea thereafter was abſolved from that fault. Anſ. Upon the complaint of the Chancelor the alleadged words were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the generall aſſembly: but before the mans guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines of theſe words could bee tryed, hee did abſent himſelfe: for which abſence he was preſently ſuſpended from his Miniſtry: in the nixt aſſembly he did appeare and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reaſon of his abſence to have been juſt feare and no contumacy, this hee made appeare to the aſſemblyes ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, but before his proceſſe could be brought to any iſſue, he fled away to England, where he died a fugitive never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his chardge, though no tryell of his fault was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.
<note place="margin">Maſter Blacks ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale from the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel cleered.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth proofe is Mr. Blacke his caſe: heereupon the Warner makes a long and odious narration. If wee interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat him about his ground of all theſe Stories, he can produce
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52046:21"/>no warrant but Spots-woods unprinted book: this is no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick regiſter whereupon any underſtanding man can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the writer was a profeſt enemy, to his death, of the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish diſciplin, he ſpent his life upon a Story for the diſgrace of the Presbytery and the honour of Bishops: no man who is acquainted with the life or death of that Author will build his beleefe upon his words. This whole narration is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly confuted in the hiſtoricall vindication, when the Warner is pleaſed to repeat the challenge from Iſſachars burden hee ought to have replyed ſomething after three yeares adviſement to the printed anſwer.</p>
            <p>The matter (as our regiſters beare) was shortly thus, in the yeare 1596 the Popish and malignant faction in King James his court grew ſo ſtrong that the countenance of the King towards the Church was much changed, and over all the Land great feares did daily increaſe of the overthrow of the Church diſcipline eſtablished by Law. The Miniſters in their pulpits gave free warning thereof, among others Mr. Black of Saint Andrews, a moſt gracious and faithful Paſtor, did apply his doctrine to the ſins of the time; ſome of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies delated him at Court for words injurious to the King and Queen: the words hee did deny and all his honeſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers did abſolve him by their teſtimony from theſe calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: of himſelfe hee was moſt willing to be tryed to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt before all the world, but his Brethren finding the libelled calumnies to bee only a pretence and the true inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Courtiers therein was, to ſtop the mouthes of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that the crying ſins of the time should no more bee reproved in pulpits, they adviſed him to decline the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the counſel, and appeale to the generall aſſembly, as the competent judge according to the word of God and the Lawes of Scotland, in the cauſe of doctrin; for the firſt inſtance they did never queſtion, but if any thing truely
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52046:22"/>ſeditious had been preached by a Miniſter that he for this might be called before the civill Magiſtrat and accordingly punished but that every Miniſter for the application of his doctrine according to the rules of ſcripture to the ſins of his hearers for their reclaming, should be brought before a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill court at the firſt inſtance, they thought it unreaſonable and defired the King in the nixt aſſembly might cognoſce upon the equity of ſuch a proceding. The Miniſters had many a conference with his Majeſtie upon that ſubject, often the matter was brought very neare to an amicable concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but becauſe the Miniſters refuſed to ſubſcribe a band for ſo great a ſilence as the Court required againſt his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties countenancing of treacherous Papiſts, and favouring the enemies of religion, a ſeveer Sentence was pronounced not only againſt Maſter <hi>Black,</hi> but alſo all the Miniſters of Edinburgh.</p>
            <p>In the meane time malcontented States-men did adde oyle to the flame,
<note place="margin">The tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult of the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was harmeleſſe and no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it.</note> and at the very inſtant while the Miniſters and their friends are offering a petition to his Majeſtie, they ſubborne a villane to cry in one part of the ſtreets the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are ſlain, and in another part of the ſtreets that the King was killed: whereupon the People rush all out to the ſtreets in their armes, and for halfe an howr at moſt were in a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, upon meere ignorance what the fray might be, but without the hurt of any one man: ſo ſoone as it was found that both the King and Miniſters were ſafe, the people went all peaceably to their houſes. This is the very truth of that innocent commotion, whereupon the Warner heere and his fellowes elſewhere make all their tragedies. None of the Miniſtry were either the authors or approvers thereof, though diverſe of them ſuffered ſore troubles for it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52046:22"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>No Presbyterian ever intended to excommunicat any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Magiſtrat.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Warner in his fifth chapter chardges the Scotes for ſubjecting the King to the cenſure of excommunication and bringing upon princes all the miſeries which the popes excommunications of old wont to bring upon Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed Emperours. Anſ.
<note place="margin">The prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narly, but the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery never were for raſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</note> It does not become the Warner and his fellowes to object to any the abuſe of the dreadfull ſentence of excommunication, no Church in the world was ever more guilty of that fault then the praelats of England and Ireland, did they ever cenſure their own officialls for the pronouncing of that terrible ſentence moſt profanly againſt any they would, had it been for the non-payment of the ſmalleſt ſummes of mony. As for the Scotes, their doctrine and practiſe in the point of excommunication is as conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat as any other church in the world, that cenſure in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is moſt rare and only in the caſe of obſtinacy in a great ſin: what ever be their doctrine in generall with all other Chriſtians and as I think with the praelaticall party them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the object of Chriſtian doctrine Sacraments and diſciplin is one and the ſame, and that no member of Chriſt, no ſone of the Church, may plead a highnes above admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and Church cenſures, yet I know they never thought it expedient ſo much as to intend any proceſſe of Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadverſion againſt their Soveraigne. To the worlds end I hope they shal not have againe greater grievances and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cauſes of citation from their Princes then they have had already. It may be confidently beleeved that they who upon ſo pregnant occaſions did never ſo much as intend the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52046:23"/>beginning of a proceſſe againſt their King, can never be ſuppoſed in danger of any ſuch proceeding for time to come. How ever,
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats flatter Princes to their ruine.</note> we love not the abuſed ground of the Warners flattering of Princes to their owne great hurt: is it ſo indeed that all the ſins of princes are only againſt God, that all Kings are not only above all lawes of Church and State but when they fall into the greateſt crimes that the worſt of men have ever committed, that even then their ſins muſt not be againſt any man or againſt any law? ſuch Epiſcopall doctrin ſpurrs on princes to theſe unhappy praecipies, and oppreſſed people unto theſe outrages that both fall into inextricable calamities.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>It grieves the Praelats that Presbyterians are faithfull Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to admonish Princes of their duty.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE ſixth Chapter is ſpent on an other crime of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery;
<note place="margin">The Scots Miniſters preaching for juſtice, was juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</note> it makes the Presbiters cry to the Magiſtrat for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon capitall offenders. Anſ. What hes Presbytery to doe with this matter were it never ſo great an offence: will the Warner have all the faults of the praelaticall faction, flow from the fountaine of Epiſcopacy? this unconſequentiall reaſoning will not be permitted to men below the degrees of Doctors. But was it a very great crime indeed for Miniſters to plead the cauſe of the fatherleſſe and widowes, yea the cauſe of God their Maſter and to preach unto Magiſtrats, that according to Scriptures murtherers ought to die, and the Land bee purged from the ſtaine of innocent blood? when the shamefull impunity of murther made Scotland by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52046:23"/>deadly fends, in time of peace a feild of warre and blood, was it not time for the faithfull ſervants of God to exhort the King toexecute juſtice, and to declare the danger of moſt frequent pardons drawne from his hand often againſt his heart by the importunity and deceitfull information of powerfull ſolicitors, to the great offence of God againſt the whole land, to the unexpreſſible griefe and wrong of the ſuffering party, to the opening alſo of a new floodgate of more blood which by a legall revenge in time eaſily might have been ſtopped? Too much pitty in ſparing the wilfull shedders of innocent blood ordinarlie proves a great cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not only to wards the diſconſolat oppreſſed who cry to the vicegerents of God the avenger, for juſtice in vaine, but alſo towards the ſoule of him who is ſpared and the life of many more who are friends either to the oppreſſor or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p>As for the named caſe of Huntly let the world judge,
<note place="margin">Huntlyes notorious crymes.</note> whether the Miniſters had reaſon often to give Warning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that wicked man and his complices. Beſide his apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacy and after-ſeeming-repentance his frequent relapſes into avowed popery, in the eighty eight he banded with the King of Spaine to overthrow the religion and government of the whole Iland and after pardon, from time to time did renew his treaſonable plots for the ruine of Britain: hee did commit many murders, he did invade under the noſe of the King, the houſe of his Couſin the Earle of Murray, and moſt cruelly murdered that gallant Nobleman, hee appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with diſplayed Banner againſt the King in perſon, he killed thereafter many hundreds of the Kings good people, when theſe multiplyed outrages did cry up to the God of heaven, was is not time for the men of God to cry to the jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the earth to doe their duty, according to the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of many Scriptures? what a dangerous humour of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52046:24"/>is this in our Praelats, not only to lull aſleep a Prince in a moſt ſinfull neglect of his charge, but alſo to cry out upon others more faithfull then themſelves for aſſaying to breake of their ſlumber by their wholeſome and ſeaſonable admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions from the word of God?</p>
            <p>The nixt challenge of the Scotes Presbyters is that they ſpoile the King of his Tythes,
<note place="margin">Never any queſtion in Scotland betwixt the King and the Church, for Tythes and patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages.</note> firſt fruits, patronage and dependence of his ſubjects. Anſ. The Warner underſtands not what he writes, the Kings Majeſtie in Scotland never had, never craved any firſt fruits: the Church never ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the King of any Tythes, ſome other men indeed, by the wickedneſſe moſt of Praelats and their followers, did cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin both the King and the Church of many Tythes: but his Majeſtie and the Church had never any controverſie in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land about the Tythes: for the King, ſo far as concerned himſelfe, was ever willing that the Church should enjoy that which the very act of Parliament acknowledgeth to bee her patrimony. Nor for the patronages had the Church any plea with the King: the Church declared often their minde of the iniquity of patronages, wherein they never had from the King any conſiderable oppoſition, but from the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and gentry the oppoſition was ſo great, that for peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Church was content to let patronages alone, till God should make a Parliament lay to heart what was incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent for gracious men to doe, for liberating congregations from their ſlavery of having Miniſters intruded upon them by the violence of Patrones. Which now at laſt (bleſſed be God) according to our mind is performed. As for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence of any vaſſals upon the King,
<note place="margin">King Iames a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowes himſelfe a hater of Eraſtianiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> it was never que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned by any Presbyterian in Scotland.</p>
            <p>What is added in the reſt of the Chapter, is but a repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which went before, to wit, the Presbyters deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King the ſpirituall government of the Church,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52046:24"/>and the power of the keyes of the Kingdome of heaven: ſuch an uſurpation upon the Church, King James declared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand (as at length may be ſeen in the Hiſtoricall vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication) to be a ſinne againſt the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which puts in the hand of the Magiſtrat the power of preaching and celebrating the Sacraments: a power which ſince that time no Magiſtrat in Britaine did aſſume, and if any would have claimed it, none would have more oppoſed, then the moſt zealous patrones of Epiſcopacy. The injurious invectives, which the Warner builds upon this his Eraſtian aſſertion, wee paſſe them as Caſtles in their aire, which muſt fall and evanish for want of a foundation. Only before I leave this Chapter, let the Warner take a good Sentence out of the mouth of that wyſe Prince King James, to teſtifie yet farther his minde againſt Eraſtianiſme. His Majeſtie in the yeare 1617 having come in progreſſe to viſit his auncient Kingdome of Scotland, and being preſent in perſone at a publick diſputation in Theologie in the Univerſitie of St. Andrews, whereof alſo many both Nobles and Church-men of both Kingdomes were auditors; when one of thoſe that acted a part in the diſputation, had affirmed and went about to maintaine this aſſertion that the King had power to depoſe Miniſters from their Miniſteriall function. The King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as abhorring ſuch flatterie, cried out with a loud voice, <hi>Ego poſſum deponere Miniſtri caput, ſed non poſſum deponere ejus officium.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Presbyterie does not draw from the Magiſtrat any paritie of his power by the cheate of any relation.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the ſeventh chapter the Warner would cauſe men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many more of the Presbyteries uſurpations upon the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52046:25"/>civill Magiſtrate.
<note place="margin">The Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſceth only upon ſcandals, and that in ſewer civil things then the Biſhops<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courts were wont to meddle with.</note> The firſt is that all offences whatſoever are cognoſcible in the conſiſtory upon the caſe of ſcandals. Anſ. Firſt the Presbyterie makes no offence at all to come before the conſiſtory, but ſcandall alone. Secondly theſe civill offences (the ſcandall whereof comes before the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery) are but very few, and a great deale fewer than the Bishops officiall takes notice of in his conſiſtoriall court. That capitall crimes paſt over by the Magiſtrate should bee cenſured by the Church, no ſociety of Chriſtians who have any diſcipline, did ever call in queſtion. When the ſword of the Magiſtrat hes ſpared a murderer, an adulterer, a Blaſphemer; will any ingenuous, either praelaticall or popish divine, admitte of ſuch to the holy table without ſignes of repentance?</p>
            <p>The Warners ſecond uſurpation is but a branch of the firſt, that the Presbyterie drawes directly before it ſelfe the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of fraud in barganing, falſe meaſures, oppreſſion and in the caſe of Miniſters, brybing, uſury, fighting, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, &amp;c. Anſ. Is it then the Warners minde, that the notorious ſlander of ſuch groſſe ſins does not deſerve ſo much, as an Eccleſiaſtick rebooke? Shall ſuch perſons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out admonition be admitted to the holy communion? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the named caſes of fraud in barganing, falſe meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, oppreſſion, come ſo rarely before our Church-judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories that though theſe thirty yeares I have been much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in Presbyteries, yet did I never ſee, nor doe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ever I heard any of theſe three caſes brought before any church aſſembly. In the perſone of Miniſters, I grant, theſe faults which the canons of the Church in all times and places make the cauſes of deprivation are cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſced upon in Presbyteries, but with the good liking (I am ſure) of all both papiſts and praelats, who themſelves are free of ſuch vices. And why did not the Warner put in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52046:25"/>the cauſes of church mens deprivation from office and benefite, adultery, gluttonny and drunkennes? are theſe in his, &amp;c. which he will not have cognoſcible by the Church in the perſons of Bishops and Doctors?</p>
            <p>The Warners third challenge amounts to an high crime, that Presbyterian Miniſters are bold to preach upon theſe ſcriptures which ſpeake of the Magiſtrats duty in his office, or dare offer to reſolve from ſcripture any doubt, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexeth the conſcience of Magiſtrats or people, of Husband or Wife, of Maſter or Servant, in the diſcharge of their Chriſtian duty one to another. What ever hath been the negligence of the Bishop of Derry, yet I am ſure, all the preaching Praelats and Doctors of England pretended a great care to goe about theſe uncontroverted parts of their miniſterial function, and yet without medling with the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of State, or the depths of any mans particulare vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; much leſſe with thejudgement of juriſdiction in politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or aeconomicall cauſes.</p>
            <p>As for the Churches declaration againſt the Late engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<note place="margin">The Churches proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the late enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement cleered from miſtakes.</note> did it not well become them to ſignify their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſo great a caſe of conſcience, eſpecially when the Parliament did propone it to them for reſolution, and when they found a conjunction driven on with a cleerly malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant partie, contrary to ſolemne oathes and covenants, unto the evident hazard of Religione and them who had been moſt eminent inſtruments of its preſervation; was it not the churches duty to give warning againſt that ſinne, and to exhort the ring leaders therein to repentance?</p>
            <p>But our Warner muſt needs inſiſt upon that unhappy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and faſten great blame upon the Church for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any advice about it. Anſ. Muſt it be Jeſuiſitiſme, and a drawing of all the civill affaires to the Churches barre <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> for an aſſembly to give their advice
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52046:26"/>in a moſt eminent and important caſe of conſcence, when earneſtly called upon in a multitude of ſupplications from the moſt of the Congregations under their charge; yea when required by the States of the Kingdome in ſeverall expreſſe meſſages for that end? It ſeemes, its our Warners concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Magiſtrat would draw all the Churches in his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to a moſt unlawfull warre, for the advancement of the greateſt impiety and unjuſtice poſſible, wherein nothing could be expected by all who were engaged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in but the curſe of God; if in this caſe a doubting Natione should deſire the aſſemblies counſel for the ſtate of their ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or if the Magiſtrate would put the Church to declare what were lawfull or unlawfull according to the word of God, that it were neceſſary heer for the ſervants of God to be altogether ſilent, becauſe indeed warre is ſo civill a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that nothing in it concernes the ſoule, and nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it may be cleered by any light from the word of God.</p>
            <p>The truth is, the Church in their publick papers to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, declared oftner then once, that they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, but for an engagement, if ſo that Chriſtian and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treaties could not have obtained reaſon, and all the good people in Scotland were willing enough to have hazarded their lives and eſtates, for vindicating the wrongs done, not by the Kingdome of England, but by the ſectarian party there, againſt God the King, covenant and both Kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: but to the great griefe of their hearts, their hands were bound and they forced to ſit ſtill, and by the over great cunning of ſome, the erroneous mis-perſwaſions of others and the rash praecipitancy of it, that engagement was ſo ſpoiled in the ſtating and mannaging, that the moſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with peace of conſcience could not goe along nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any other to take part therein. The Warner touches on three of their reaſons: but who will looke upon their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52046:26"/>declarations, shall find many more, which with all faithfullneſſe were then propounded by the Church, for the rectifying of that action, which, as it ſtood in the ſtate and managment, was cleerly foretold to be exceeding like to deſtroy the King and his friends of all ſorts in all the three Kingdomes. The irreparable loſſes and unutterable cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which quickly did follow at the heeles, the misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe and contempt of the Lords ſervants and the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger religion is now brought unto in al theſe Kingdomes, hes, I ſuppoſe, long agoe brought griefe enough to the heart of them whoſe unadviſed rashnes and intemperate fervour did contribute moſt for the ſpoiling of that deſigne.</p>
            <p>The firſt deſire about that engagement which the Warner gives to us, concernes the ſecurity of religion. In all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of that matter, it was aggreed (without queſtion upon all hands, that the Sectarian party deſerved punishment for their wicked attemptes upon the Kings perſone, contrary to the directions of the Parliamentes of both Kingdomes, and that the King ought to be reſcued out of their hands, and brought to one of his houſes for perfecting the treaty of peace which often had been begunne: but here was the queſtion; Whither the Parliament and Army of Scotland ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their reſolutiones to bring his Majeſtie to London with honour, freedome and ſafty, before he did promiſe any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for eſtablishing Religion; The Parliaments of both Kingdomes in all their former treaties had ever preſſed upon the King a number of propoſitions to be ſigned by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie before at all he came to London: was it then any fault in the Church of Scotland to deſire the granting but of one of theſe propoſitions concerning Religion and the covenant, before the King were brought (by the new hazard of the lives and eſtats of all the Scottish nation) to ſit in his Parliament in that honnor and freedome which himſelfe did deſire? There
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52046:27"/>was no complaint, when many of thirty propoſitions were preſſed to be ſigned by his Majeſtie for ſatisfaction and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to his people, after ſo great and long deſolations: how then is an out-cry made, when all other propoſitions are poſtponed, and only one for Religion is ſtuck upon, and that not before his Majeſties reſcue and deliverance from the hands of the ſectaries, but only before his bringing to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in honor freedom and ſafety? This demande, to the Warner, is a crime, and may be ſo to all of his beleefe, who takes it for a high unjuſtice, to reſtraine in any King the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power by any condition: for they doe mantaine that the adminiſtration of all things both of Church and ſtate does reſide ſo freely and abſolutly in the meere will of a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, that no caſe at any time can fall out, which ought to bound that abſolutneſſe with any limitation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular the Warner pitches upon, is the Kings negative voyce; behold how criminous we were in the point; When ſome (moſt needleſly) would needs bring into debate the Kings negative voyce in the Parliament of England, as one of the royall praerogatives to bee maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by our engagement: it was ſaid, that all diſcourſe of that kynde might bee laid aſide as impertinent for us: if any debate should chance to fall upon it, the proper place of it was, in a free Parliament of England; that our Lawes did not admit of a negative voyce to the King in a Parliament of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; and to preſſe it now as a prerogative of all Kings, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the reflection it might have upon the rights of our Kingdome,) it might put in the hand of the King a power to deny all and every one of theſe things, which the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of both Kingdomes had found neceſſary for the ſetling the peace in all the three dominions. Wee marvail not, that the Warner heere should taxe us of a great errour, ſeeing it is the beleefe of his faction, that every King hath not onely
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52046:27"/>a negative but an abſolute affirmative voyce in all their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, as if they were nothing but their arbitrary coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels for to perſwade by their reaſons but not to conclude nor impede any thing by their votes; the whole and intire power of making or refuſing Lawes being in the Prince alone, and no part of it in the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Warners third challenge againſt us about the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, as if the Church had taken upon it to nominate the officers of the army; and upon this he makes his invectives. Anſ. The Church was farre from ſeeking power to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate any one officer: but the matter was thus; when the State did require of them, what in their judgement would give ſatisfaction to the people, and what would encourage them to goe along in the ingagement? one and the laſt parte of their anſwer was, that they conceived if a Warre shalbe found neceſſarie, much of the peoples encouragement would depend upon the qualification of the commanders, to whom the mannaging of that great truſt should be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for after the right ſtating of the Warre, the nixt would be the carying on of it by ſuch men who had given conſtante proofe of their integrity. To put all the power of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in their hande, whoſe by paſt miſcariadges had given juſt occaſion to ſuſpect their deſignes and firmeneſſe to the intereſt of God before their owne or any other mans, would fill the hearts of the people with jealouſies and feares, and how wholſome an advice this was, experience hath now too cleerly demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>To make the world know our further reſolutiones to medle with civile affaires, the Warner is pleaſed to bring out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us above 80 yeares old ſtories, and all the ſtuffe which our malicious enemy Spotſewood can furnish to him: from this good author he alledges that our Church diſcharged merchants to traffique with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and commanded the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52046:28"/>change of the mercat dayes in <hi>Edenburgh.</hi> Anſ. Both theſe calumnies are taken of at length in the Hiſtoricall Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. After the <hi>Spanish</hi> invaſion of the yeare eighty eight, many in Scotland kept correſpondence with <hi>Spaine</hi> for treacherous deſignes: the Inquiſitors did ſeduce ſome, and perſecute others of our merchants in their traffique, the Church did deale with his Majeſtie to interceed with the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> King for more liberty to our country men in their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and in the meane time while an anſwer was returned from <hi>Madrile,</hi> they advertiſed the people to be warry, how they hazarded their ſoules for any worldly gaine which they could find about the inquiſitors feet.</p>
            <p>As for the mercat dayes,
<note place="margin">The Church medled not with the mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat but by way of ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> I grante, it was a great griefe to the Church, to ſee the fabbath day profaned by handy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and journeying, by occaſion of the munday-mercats in the moſt of the great tounes: for remedie heerof, many ſupplications have been made by the Aſſembly to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: but ſo long as our Bishops ſatte there, theſe peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones of the Church were alwayes eluded: for the praelats labour in the whole Iland was to have the ſunday no Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and to procure by their Doctrine and example the profanation of that day by all ſorts of playes, to the end people might be brought back to their old licentiouſnes and ignorance, by which the Epiſcopall Kingdome was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. It was viſible in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that the moſt eminent Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops were uſual players on the Sabbath, even in time of divine ſervice. And ſo ſoone as they were caſt out of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the Churches ſupplications were granted, and acts obtained for the carefull ſanctification of the Lords day, and removing of the mercats in all the land from the Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to other dayes of the week.</p>
            <p>The Warners nixt challenge of our uſurpation is, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly at Edinburgh 1567 their ratifying of acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52046:28"/>and ſummoning of all the country to appeare at the nixt aſſembly.
<note place="margin">The Church once for ſafty of the infant Kings life, with the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the ſecrete counſel did cal an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Anſ. If the Warner had knowne the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that time, he would have choyſed rather to have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this challenge, then to have proclaimed to the world the great rottenneſſe of his own heart; at that time the condition of the Church and Kingdome of Scotland was lamentable, the Queen was declared for popery, King James's Father was cruelly without any cauſe murthered by the Earle of Bothwell; King James himſelfe in his infancy was very neare to have been deſtroyed by the murtherer of his Father, there was no other way conceivable of ſaftie for Religion for the infant King, for the Kingdome, but that the Proteſtantes should joine together for the defence of King James againſt theſe popish murtherers. For this end the generall aſſembly did crave conference of the ſecrete counſel: and they with mutual adviſe did call for a meeting of the whole Proteſtant party: which did conveen at the time appointed moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in an extraordinary and mixed aſſembly of all the conſiderable perſons of the Religion, Earles, Lords, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes and Miniſters, and ſubſcribed a bond for the revenge of King <hi>Henryes</hi> death, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of King <hi>Iames</hi> his life: This mixed and extraordinary aſſembly made it one of the chiefe articles in their bond to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend theſe Actes of the Parliament 1560 concerning religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to endeavour the ratification of them in the nixt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Parliament. As for the aſſemblies letter to their Brethren for ſo frequent a meeting at the nixt extraordinary aſſembly, it had the authority of the ſecret counſel; it was in a time of the greateſt neceſſity, when the Religion and liberties of the land were in evident hazard from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and wicked counſels of the popish party, both at home and abroad; when the life of the young King was daily in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible danger from the hands of them who had murthered his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52046:29"/>Father, and ravished his Mother. Leſſe could not have been done in ſuch a juncture of time by men of wiſedom and courage, who had any love to their Religion, King and country: but the reſolution of our praelats is to the contrary, when a moſt wicked villaine had obtained the connivance of a Queen to kill her husband, and to make way for the killing of her Son in his Cradle, and after theſe murders to draw a nation &amp; Church from the true Religion, eſtablished by Law, into popery; and a free Kingdome to an illegall Tyranny; in this caſe there may be no meeting, either of Church or State, to provide remedies againſt ſuch extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary miſchiefes. Beleeve it, the <hi>Scotes</hi> were never of this opinion.</p>
            <p>What is ſubjoined in the nixt paragraph of our Churches praeſumption to abolish acts of Parliament;
<note place="margin">By the lawes and cuſtomes of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the Aſſembly praecieds the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Eccleſias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> is but a repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what is ſpoken before. Not only the lawes of <hi>Scotland</hi> but equity and neceſſity referres the ordinary reformation of errours and abuſes in Religion to the Eccleſiaſticall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies: what they find wrong in the Church, though ratified by acts of Parliament, they rectify it from the word of God, and thereafter by petition obtaines their rectification to be ratifyed in a following Parliament, and all former acts to the contrary to be annulled. This is the ordinary Methode of proceeding in <hi>Scotland</hi> and (as I take it) in all other States and Kingdomes. Were Chriſtians of old hindred to leave paganisme and embrace the Goſpell, till the emperiall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes for paganisme and againſt Chriſtianity were revoked? did the oecumenicall and National Synods of the auncients ſtay their reformation of hereſies and corruptions in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, till the lawes of State (which did countenance theſe errors) were cancelled? Was not popery in <hi>Germany France</hi> and <hi>Britaine</hi> ſo firmely eſtablished, as civil lawes could doe it? It ſeems, the Warner heer does joyne with his Brother
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52046:29"/>
               <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> to proclaime all our Reformers in <hi>Britaine France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> to be Rebells for daring by their preachings and Aſſemblies to change theſe things, which by acts of Parliaments had been approven, before new Parliaments had allowed of their reformation. Nevertheleſſe this plea is foolishly intended againſt us, for the Miniſters proteſtation againſt the acts of Parliament 1584, eſtablishing (in that houre of darknes) iniquity by a law, and againſt the acts of the Aſſembly of Glasgow declaring the unlawfulneſſe of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and ceremonies; which ſome Parliaments upon Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall mis-information had approven: both theſe actions of the Church were according to former Lawes and were rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied afterward by acts of Parliament yet ſtanding in force which for the Warner (a privatman, and a ſtranger) to challenge, is to contemne much more grosſly the law, then they doe, whom here he is accuſing of that crime.</p>
            <p>By the nixt Story the Warner will gaine nothing,
<note place="margin">The Church parte in the road of Ruth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> when the true caſe of it is knowne. In King <hi>Iames</hi> minority, one Captaine <hi>Iames Stuart</hi> did ſo farre prevail upon the tender and unexperienced yeares of the Prince, as to ſteale his countenance unto acts of the greateſt oppreſſion; ſo farre that <hi>Iames Hamelton</hi> Earle of Arran (the nixt to the King in blood, in his health a moſt gallant Prince, and a moſt zealous profeſſor of the true Religion) in time of his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, when he was not capable to commit any crime againſt the State, was notwithſtanding ſpoiled of all his livelyhood and liberty: his Lands and honour with the dignity of high Chancelor of <hi>Scotland</hi> were conferred on that very wicked Tyrant Captain <hi>Iames,</hi> a number of the beſt affected and prime nobility impatient of ſuch unheard-of oppreſſiones, with meere boaſts and no violence at the road of Ruthven chaſed away that unhappy chancelor from the Kings perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, this his Majeſtie for the time profeſſed to take in ſo good
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52046:30"/>part that under his hand he did allow it for good ſervice, in his letters to the moſt of the Neighbour princes: he dealt alſo with the ſecrete counſel and the chiefe judicatories of the land, and obtained from them the approbation of that act of the Lords as convenient and laudable, promiſing likewiſe to ratify it in the nixt enſuing Parliament. When the Lords for their more abundante cleering required the Aſſemblies declaration there upon, the Miniſters declined to medle at all with the caſe; but the Kings Majeſtie ſent his Commiſſioners to the Aſſembly, entreating them withall earneſtneſſe to declare their good liking of that action, which he aſſured them was for his good, and the good both of the Church and Kingdome: for their obedience to the Kings importunity they are heer railed upon by the wiſe Warner. It is true, Captaine <hi>Iames</hi> shortly after creept in againe into Court, and obtained a ſever revenge againſt the authors of that action, before a Parliament could ſit to approve it, but within a few monthes the ſame Lords with ſome more did at <hi>Striveling</hi> chaſe againe that evill man from the Court: whither he never more returned, and this their action was ratified in the nixt Parliament, and ſo ſtands to this day unqueſtioned by any but ſuch as the Warner, either out of ignorance or malice.</p>
            <p>I am weary to follow the Warner in all his wandrings;
<note place="margin">The inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the generall aſſembly of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of England.</note> at the nixt loupe he jumps from the 1584 to the 1648, skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping over in a moment 64 yeares. The articles of <hi>Strive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> mentions that the promoving of the worke of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in England and Ireland, bee referred to the generall aſſembly, upon this our friend does diſcharge a flood of his choler: all the matter of his impatience heere is, that Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land when by fraud they had been long allured, and at laſt by open violence invaded by the English Praelats, that they might take on the yock of all their corruptions, they were
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52046:30"/>contented at the earneſt deſire of both the houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all the wel-affected in England, to aſſiſt their Brethren, to purge out the leaven of Epiſcopacy, and the Service book with all the reſt of the old corruptions of the English and Irish Churches; with the mannaging of this ſo great and good an Eccleſiaſtick worke, the Parliament of Scotland did intruſt the generall aſſembly. No mervaile that <hi>Doctor Bramble</hi> a zealous lover of all the Arminianiſme, Popery and Tyranny, of which his great patron <hi>Doctor Lade</hi> ſtands convicted yet without an anſwer to have been brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in upon the three nations, should bee angry at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverers and diſ-appointers of that moſt pious work as they wont to ſtyle it?</p>
            <p>What heere the Warner repeats, it is anſwered before,
<note place="margin">The vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Maſſe-Prieſts Prieſts in their act of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Warner.</note> as for the two Storyes in his concluſion, which he takes out of his falſe Author Spots-wood, adding his owne large am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifications; I conceive, there needs no more to be ſaid to the firſt, but that ſome of <hi>Iohn Knocks</hi> zealous hearers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of a Maſſe-Prieſt at their very ſide committing idolatry contrary to the Lawes, did with violence break in upon him and ſeaſe upon his perſon and Maſſe-cloathes, that they might preſent him to the ordinary Magiſtrat to receave juſtice according to the Law; This act the Warner wil have to be a huge rebellion, not only in the actors, but alſo in <hi>Iohn Knocks,</hi> who was not ſo much as preſent thereat.</p>
            <p>What firſt he ſpeaks of the Aſſemblies convocating the people in armes to be preſent at the tryall of the popish Lords and their avowing of that their deed to the King in his face we muſt be pardoned to miſtruſt the Warner heerin upon his bare word without the releefe of ſome witnes, and that a more faithfull one then his Brother in evill, Mr. Spotswood, whom yet heere he does not profeſſe to cite. Againſt theſe popish Lords after their many treaſons and bloody murders
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52046:31"/>of the lieges, the King himſelfe at laſt was forced to arme the people; but that the generall aſſembly did call any unto armes we require the Warners proofe that we may give it an anſwer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The chiefe of the Praelats agree with the Presbyterians about the divine right of Church diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Warners challenge in this chapter is that we man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our diſcipline by a <hi>Iure divino,</hi> and for this he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes out upon us a ſea of ſuch rhetorick, as much better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemed. Anſ. <hi>Mercurius Aulicus</hi> then either a Warner or a praelate. In this challenge he is as unhappy as in the reſt, it is for a matter wherein the moſt of his owne Brethren (though our Adverſaries) yet fully agree with us that the diſcipline of the Church is truely by divine right,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and his Praelatical Eraſtian brethren are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by their owne principles to adviſe the King to lay aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy and ſet up the Praesbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in all his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and that Jeſus Chriſt holds out in ſcripture the ſubſtantials of that Governement whereby he will have his houſe to be ruled to the worlds end; leaving the circumſtantials to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the judicatories of the Church according to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rules, which are clear alſo in the word for matters of that nature. In this neither Papiſts nor the learndeſt of the Praelats find any fault with us; yet our Warner muſt ſpend a whole Chapter upon it.</p>
            <p>It is true as we obſerved before the elder Praelats of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in <hi>Edwards</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, as the Eraſtians now, did mantaine that no particular Governement of the Church was <hi>jure divino,</hi> and if this be the Warners mind, it were ingenuity in him to ſpeake it out loud, and to endeavour
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52046:31"/>to perſwade his friends about the King of the truth of this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, he was never imployed about a better and more ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſervice: for if the diſcipline of the Church be but <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano jure</hi> then Epiſcopacy is keeped up upon no conſcience, conſcience being bottomed only upon a divine right, ſo Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy wanting that bottom may well be laid aſide at this time by the King for any thing that concernes conſcience ſince no command of God nor warrant from ſcripture tyes him to keep it up. This truely ſeemes to be the maine ground whereupon the whole diſcourſe of this Chapter is builded. Is it tolerable that ſuch truthes should be concealed by our Warners againſt their conſcience, when the ſpeaking of them out might be ſo advantagious to the King and all his Kingdomes, how ever wee with all the reformed Churches doe beleeve in our heart the divine right of Synods and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries, and for no poſſible inconvenient can be forced to deny or paſſe from this part of truth, yet the Warner heere joynes with the elder Praelats who till Warner <hi>Banckrofts</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to the ſea of Canterburry did unanimouſly deny Epiſcopacy to be of divine right, and by conſequent affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it to be moveable, and ſo lawfull to be laid aſide by princes, when ſo ever they found it expedient for their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires to be quyte of it, why does not the warner and his Brethren ſpeake plainly their thoughts in his Majeſties eares? why do they longer diſſemble their conſcience, only for the ſatisfaction of their ambition, greed, and revenge? ſundry of the Praelaticall divines come yet further to joyne fully with Eraſtus in denying not only Epiſcopacy and all other particular formes of Church government to be of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution, but in avowing that no governement in the Church at all is to be imagined, but ſuch as is a part of the civill power of the Magiſtrat. The Warner in the Chapter and in diverſe other parts of his booke ſeemes to agree with
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52046:32"/>this judgment: and upon this ground if he had ingenuity he would offer his helping hand to untie the bonds of the Kings conſcience, if heere it were ſtraytened, by demonſtrating from this his principle, that very ſafely without any offence to God and nothing doubting for conſcience ſake, his Majeſtie might lay aſide Epiſcopacy and ſet up the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſo fully as is required in all his dominions though not upon a divine right which the Presbyterians beleeve, yet upon Eraſtus royall right which the Warner here and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where avouches.</p>
            <p>What the Warner puts heere again upon the Presbyterie,
<note place="margin">The prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall party were late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent for Popery.</note> the uſurpation of the temporall ſword in what indirect rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo ever, its probation in the former chapter was found ſo weake and naughty, that the repetition of it is for no uſe: only wee marke that the Warner will have the Presbitery to be an abſolute papacy, for no other purpoſe but to vent his deſire of revenge againſt the Presbyterians, who gave in a challenge againſt the Praelats, eſpecially the late Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, among whom <hi>Doctor Bramble</hi> was one of ſome note, to which none of them have returned to this howre an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; that their principles unavoidably did bring backe the pope. For a Patriarch over all the weſterne Churches, and among all the Patriarches of the whole Catholick Church a primacy in the <hi>Roman,</hi> flowes cleerly out of the fountaine of Epiſcopacy, according to the avowed doctrine of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish praelats: who yet are more liberall to the pope in gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him beſide his ſpirituall ſuper-inſpection of the whole Catholick Church, all his temporall juriſdictions alſo in the patrimony of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peter, and all his other faire principalities within and without Italy. There is no ceremony in <hi>Rome</hi> that theſe men ſtick upon: for of all the ſuperſtitious and idolatrous ceremonies of <hi>Rome,</hi> their images and altars and adorations before them are incomparably the worſt; yet
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52046:32"/>the Warners friends without any recantation we have heard of, avow them all; even an adoration of and to the altar it ſelfe. As for the doctrines of <hi>Rome</hi> what points are worſe then theſe which that party have avowed in expreſſe tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, a corporall preſence of Chriſts body upon the Altar the Tridentine juſtification, free-will, finall apoſtacy of the Saints: when no other thing can be anſwered to this our ſore challenge, it is good to put us off with a Squib that the Presbyterie is as abſolute papacy as ever was in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Presbyterian poſition which the Warner heere offers not to diſpute but to laugh at, that Chriſt as King of his Church according to his royall office and Scepter hes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the office bearers and lawes of the houſe, is accorded to by the moſt and sharpeſt of our adverſaries, whether En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish or Romish, as their owne tenet: howbeit ſuch foolish conſequences, that all acts of Synods muſt be Chriſts Lawes, &amp;c. neither they nor wee doe acknowledge.</p>
            <p>His declamations againſt the novelty of the Presbyterie in the ordinary ſtile of the Jeſuites againſt Proteſtants,
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe now a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolish at leaſt three parts of the former Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> and of the pagan Philoſophers againſt the Chriſtians of old, who will regarde: our plea for the Praesbyterie is, that it is ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; if ſo; it is auncient enough: if not; let it be abolished. But it were good, that heer alſo the Warner and his friends would be ingenuous, to ſpeake out their minds of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Why have they all ſo long deceived the King, in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him that English Episcopacy was wel warranted both by Scripture and antiquity. Be it ſo (which yet is very falſe) that ſomething of a Bishop diſtinct from a Presbyter had any footing in Scripture, yet can they be ſo impudent, as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that an English Bishop in his very flesh and blood, in his ſubſtantiall limbs was ever knowne in the World till the pope was become Antichriſt? A Bishop by virtue of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice a Lord in Parliament, voycing in all acts of State, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52046:33"/>exerciſing the place of a high Theſaurer, of a Chancelor, or what ever civill charge the favour of a Prince did put upon him; a Bishop with ſole power of ordination and juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with out any Presbytery; a Bishop exerciſing no ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction himſelfe in any part of his dioces, but devolving the exerciſe of that power wholly upon his officials &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries; a Bishop ordaining Presbyters himſelfe alone, or with the fashionall aſſiſtance of any two Presbyters, who chaunce to be neare; a Bishop the only Paſtor of the whole dioces, and yet not bound to feed any flock, either by word or Sacrament, or governement, but having a free liberty to devolve all that ſervice upon others, and himſelf to wayte at court ſo many yeares as he shall think fit. This is our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Bishop not only in practiſe but in law, and ſo was hee defended by the great diſputants for praelacy in England.</p>
            <p>But now let the Warner ſpeake out,
<note place="margin">The porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, which yet is ſtuck to, cannot be kept up upon any principle either of honour or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> if any ſuch treaſure can more be defended or was ever knowne in ſcripture, or ſeen in any Chriſtian Church for 800. yeares and above, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of Chriſt. I take it indeed, to be conſcience, that forces now at laſt the beſt of our Court-divines to deveſt their Bishop of all civill imployment in Parliament court or Kingdome, in denying his ſolitarines in ordination, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving his officiall and Commiſſary courts, in taking away all his arches, Arch-Bishops, Arch-Deacons, deane and Chapter and all the, &amp;c. in erecting Presbyteries for all ordinations and ſpirituall jurisdiction. It is good that conſcience moves our adverſaries at laſt to come this farre towards us: butwhy will they not yet come nearer, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that by theſe their to lately recanted errours they did to long trouble the world; and that the little which yet they deſire to keepe of a Bishop is nothing leſſe then that English Bishop but a new creature of their own deviſing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known in England which his Majeſtie in no honnour is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52046:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>obliged to mantaine for any reſpect either to the lawes or cuſtomes of England, and leaſt of all, for conſcience?</p>
            <p>While the Warner with ſuch confidence avowes,
<note place="margin">The ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the moſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy is contrary to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> that no text of Scripture can be alleadged againſt Epiſcopacy, which may not with more reaſon be applyed againſt the Presbytery; behold I offer him here ſome few, caſting them in a couple of arguments, which according to his great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, I wish, he would anſwer at his leaſure.</p>
            <p>Firſt I doe reaſon from Epheſians 4.11: all the officers that Chriſt has appointed in his Church for the Miniſtry of the word, are either Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors or Doctors: but Bishops are none of theſe fyve: Ergo they are none of the officers appointed by Chriſt for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the word. The Major is not wonte to be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: the minor thus I prove; Bishops are not Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, nor prophets: for its confeſſed, all theſe were extraordinary and temporary officers: but Bishops (ſay yow) are ordinary and perpetuall: our adverſaries pitch upon the fourth, alleadging the Epiſcopall office to be paſtorall; but I prove the Bishop no Paſtor thus; no Paſtor is ſuperior to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſtors in any ſpirituall power: but according to our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, a Bishop is ſuperior to all the Paſtors of his dioces in the power of ordination and juriſdiction. Ergo. The doubt heer is only of the Major, which I prove <hi>Argumento à pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> no Apoſtle is ſuperior to an Apoſtle, nor an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts to an Evangeliſt, nor prophet to a prophet nor a Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to a Doctour in any ſpirituall power according to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Ergo no Paſtor to a Paſtor. Againe I reaſon from 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Math:</hi> 18.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.12.13, What taks the power of ordination and jurisdiction from Bishops, deſtroyes Bishops: as the removall of the ſoule kills the man, and the denyall of the forme takes away the ſubject; ſo the power of ordination and juriſdiction the eſſentiall forme, whereby the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52046:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>Bishop is conſtitute and diſtinguished from the Presbyter and every other Church officer, being removed from him, he muſt perish: but the quoted places take away cleerly theſe powers from the Bishop: for the firſt puts the power of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination in the Presbytery, and a Bishop is not a Presbytery; the ſecond puts the power of juriſdiction in the Church; and the third in a company of men which meet together: but the Bishop is not the Church nor a company of men met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for theſe be many, and he is but one perſone.</p>
            <p>When the Doctors learning he; ſatisfied us in theſe two, he shall receave more ſcripturall arguments againſt Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their oppoſits.</note> But why doe wee expect anſwers from theſe men, when after ſo long time (for all their boaſts of learning and their viſible leaſure) none of their party hes hade the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to offer one word of anſwer to the Scriptures and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which in great plenty Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> and Mr. <hi>Didoclave</hi> of old, and of late that mitacle of learning moſt noble <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais,</hi> and that Magazin of antiquity Mr. <hi>Blondel</hi> have prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt them?</p>
            <p>What in the end of the Chapter the Warner addes of our trouble at King James his fiftie and five queſtions 1596, and of our yeelding the bucklers without any oppoſition till the late unhappy troubles; we anſwer that in this as every where elſe the Warner proclaines his great and certaine knowledge of our Eccleſiaſtick ſtory: the troubles of the Scots divines at that time were very ſmall, for the matter of theſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all which they did anſwer ſo roundly, that ther was no more ſpeach of them therafter by the propounders: but the manner and time of theſe queſtions did indeed perplex good men, to ſee Eraſtian and Prelaticall counſellors ſo farr to prevaile with our King, as to make him by captious queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons carpe at theſe parts of Church-diſcipline, which by ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuts of Parliament and acts of Aſſemblyes were fully eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52046:34"/>
            <p> Our Church at that time was far from yeelding to Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy:
<note place="margin">Prelacy was ever grievous to Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> great trouble indeed by ſome wicked States-men was then brought upon the perſones of the moſt able and faithfull Miniſters, but our land was ſo far from receiving of Bishops at that time, that the queſtion was not ſo much as propoſed to them for many yeares thereafter, it was in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1606 that the English Praelats did move the King by great violence to caſt many of the beſt and moſt learned Preachers of Scotland out of their charges, and in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1610, that a kind of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy was ſet up in the corrupt aſſembly of <hi>Glaſgow;</hi> under which the Church of Scotland did heavily groane till the yeare 1637, when their burdens was ſo much increaſed by the English praelaticall Tax-maſters, that all was shaken of together, and divine juſtice did ſo cloſly follow at the heeles, that oppreſſing praelacy of England as to the great joy of the long oppreſſed Scotes, that evill root and all its branches was caſt out of <hi>Britaine,</hi> where wee truſt, no shadow of it shall ever againe be ſeen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Common-wealth is no monſter, when God is made So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, and their commands of men are ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the clear will of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving cleered the vanity of theſe calumnious challenges, where with the Warner did animate the King and all Magiſtrates againſt the Presbyterians, let us try if his skill be any greater, to inflame the people againſt it. Hee would make the World beleeve that the Presbyterians are great tranſſubſtantiators of whole Common-wealths into beaſts,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52046:35"/>and Metamorphoſers of whole Kingdomes of men, into Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents with two heads; how great and monſtrous a Serpent muſt the Presbytery be, when shee is the Mother of a Dragon with two heads. But it is good, that she has nothing to doe with the procreation of the Dragon with ſeven heads, the great Antichriſt, the Pope of <hi>Rome:</hi> this honour muſt bee left to Epiſcopacy: the Presbytery muſt not pretend to any share in it.</p>
            <p>The Warners ground for his pretty ſimilitude is,
<note place="margin">There is no Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship but a meer ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and miniſtry in the Paſtors of the Church</note> that the Presbyterians make two Soveraignities in every Chriſtian State, whoſe commands are contrary. Anſ. All the evill lyeth in the contrariety of the commands: as for the double Soveraignity, ther is no shew of truth in it: for the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians cannot bee guilty of coordinating two Soveraigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in one State, though the Praelats may wel be guilty of that fault; ſince they with there Maſters of <hi>Rome</hi> mantaine a true hierarchie, a Spirituall Lord-ship, a domination and principality in their Bishops above all the members of the Church, but the Presbyterians know no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no dominion, no Soveranity in Church officers, but a meer miniſtry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt. As for the contrariety of commands, its true: Chriſts Miniſters muſt publish all the commands of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Lord, whereunto no command of any temporall Prince needs or ought to be contrary; but if it fall out to bee ſo, it is not the Presbytery; but the holy Scriptures, which command rather to obey God then man. Dare the Warner heere oppoſe the Presbyterians? dare he mantaine a ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Church to the State in ſuch a fashion, that the cleer commands of God published by the Church ought to give place to the contrary commands of the State? if the Warner muſt needs invert and contradict Chriſt ruling of this caſe, let him goe on to preach doctrine point blank to the Apoſtles, that it is better to obey men then God. It falls
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52046:35"/>out as rarely in Scotland as any where in the world, that the Church and State run contrary wayes; but if ſo it happen, the commune rules of humane direction towards right and wrong judgement muſt be followed: if a man find either the Church or the State or both command what he knowes to be wrong (for neither the one nor the other hath any infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) their is no doubt but either or both may be diſobeyed, yet with this difference, that for diſobedience to the Churches moſt juſt commands, a man can not fall under the ſmalleſt temporall inconvenient without the States good pleaſure, but for his diſobedience to the moſt unjuſt commands of the State he muſt ſuffer what ever punishment the law does in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict without any releefe from the Church.</p>
            <p>Two inſtances are brought by the Warner, of the Church and States contrary commands: the firſt the King comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Edenburgh to feaſt the frensh Ambaſſadours, but the Church commanded Edenburgh to faſt that day when the King deſired them to feaſt. Anſ. Heer were no ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry commands, but both were obeyed, the people did kepe the humiliation, and ſome of the Magiſtrats that ſame day did give the banquet to the frensh Ambaſſadours as the King commanded; that for this any Church cenſure was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt them it is a malitious calumny, according to the author of this fable his owne confeſſion, as at length may be ſeen in the unloading of Iſſachars burden.</p>
            <p>As for his ſecond inſtance,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is ful of calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths.</note> the difference of the Church and State about the late ingagement we have ſpoken to it in the former chapter at length: the furtheſt the Church went was by humble petitions and remonſtrances to ſet before the Parliament the great danger, which that ingagement (as it was ſtated and mannaged) did portent to religion, the Kings Perſon &amp; whole Kingdom, when contrary to their whole ſome advices the ingagement went on, they medled not to oppoſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52046:36"/>the act of State further then to declare their judgement of its unlawfulneſſe, according to the duty of faithfull watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. It is very falſe that the Church has chaſed any man out of the country, or excommunicated any for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that engagement, or have put any man to ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath for it, unto his day. Neither did ever any man call the freedome of the late Parliament in queſtion, how unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied ſoever many were with its proceedings.</p>
            <p>When the Warner heapes up ſo many untruths in a few lines, in things done but yeſterday before the eyes of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, we shall not wonder of his venturing to lye conſident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in things paſt long before any now living were borne: but there are a generation of men who are bold to ſpeake what makes for their end upon the hope that few wil be at the pains, to bring back what hes flowne from their teeth to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of any ſolide tryall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Nature of the Preſbytrie is very concordant with Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the tenth chapter the Warner undertakes to shew the antipathy of Presbyteries to Parliaments; albeit there bee no greater harmony poſſible betwixt any two bodies, then betwixt a generall aſſembly and Parliament, a Presbyterie and an inferior civill court, if either the conſtitution or end or dayly practiſe of theſe judicatories be looked upon: but the praelaticall learning is of ſo high a flight, that it dare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove any concluſion: yet theſe men are not the firſt, that have offered to force men to beleeve upon unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52046:36"/>arguments though contrary to common ſence and and reaſon that ſnow is black and the fire cold and the light dark.
<note place="margin">The eight deſires of the Church about the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were juſt and neceſſary.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For the proofe of his concluſion he brings backe yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the late engagement: how often shall this inſipide col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort be ſet upon our table? Will the Warner never be filled with this unſavory dish? The firſt crime that here the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner marks in our Church againſt the late Parliament in the matter of the ingagement is, their paper of the eight deſires: upon this he unpoureth out all his good pleaſure, not willing to know that all theſe deſires were drawne from the Church by the Parliaments owne meſſages, and that well neare all theſe deſires were counted by the Parliament it ſelf to be very juſt and neceſſary: Eſpecially theſe two which the wiſe Warner pitches upon as moſt abſurd for the firſt a ſecurity to religion from the King upon oath under his hand and ſeale: where the queſtion among us was not for the thing it ſelf, but only about the time, the order and ſome part of the matter of that ſecurity. And for the ſecond, the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the perſons to be imployed, that all should be ſuch who had given no juſt cauſe of Jealouſy; no man did queſtion, but all who were to have the managing of that warre should be free of all juſt cauſes of Jealouſy, which could be made appeare not to halfe a doſſen of Miniſters, but to any competent judicatory according to the lawes of the Kingdome. The Warner has not been carefull to informe himſelfe, where the knot of the difference lay, and ſo gives out his owne groundleſſe conjectures for true Hiſtoricall narrations, which he might eaſily have helped by a more attentive reading of our publick declarations.</p>
            <p>The ſecond fault he finds with our Church is, that they proclaime in print their diſſatisfaction with that ingagement as favourable to the malignant party, &amp;c. Anſ. The
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52046:37"/>Warner knows not that it is one of the liberties of the Church of Scotland eſtablished by law and long cuſtome to keep the people by publick declarations in their duty to God,
<note place="margin">It is one of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to publish declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> when men are like to draw them away to ſin according to that of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 12.13. What in great humility piety and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was ſpoken to the world in the declaration of the Church concerning that undertaking, was viſible enough for the time to any who were not peremptor to follow their owne wayes: and the lamentable event ſince has opened the eyes of many, who before would not ſee, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their former errours: but if God should ſpeake never ſo loud from Heaven, the Warner and his party will ſtoppe their eares: for they are men of ſuch gallant Spirits, as ſcorne to ſubmit either to God or men, but in a Romane conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they will be ever the ſame though their counſels &amp; wayes be found never ſo palpably pernicious.</p>
            <p>The third thing the Warner layes to the charge of our Church is,
<note place="margin">The leavy was never offered to be ſtopped by the Church.</note> that they retarded the leavies. Anſ. In this alſo the Warner shewes his ignorance or malice: for how ſore ſoever the Levy (as then ſtated &amp; mannaged) was againſt the hearts of the Church, yet their oppoſition to it, was ſo cold-rife and ſmall, that no complaint needs bee made of any retardment from them. So ſoone as the commanders thought it expedient, there was an Army gotten up ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and ſtrong, that with the ordinary bleſſing of God was aboundantly able to have done all the profeſſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: but where the averſion of the hearts of the Church and the want of their prayers is ſuperciliouſly contemned,
<note place="margin">The Church was not the cauſe of the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering at Mauchlin Moore.</note> what mervaile, that the ſtrongeſt arme of flesh bee quickly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in peeces?</p>
            <p>The fourth charge is moſt calumnious, that the Church gathered the country together in armes at Mauchline moor to oppoſe the expedition. Anſ. No Church man was the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52046:37"/>cauſe of that meeting a number of yeomen being frighted from their houſes, did flee away to that corner of the Land, that they might not be forced againſt their conſcience to goe as ſouldiers to England: while their number did grow, and they did abide in a body for the ſecurity of their perſons, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſudden a part of the Army came upon them: ſome Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters being neare (by occaſion of the communion at Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chlin the day before) were good inſtruments with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to goe away in peace. And when the matter was tryed to the bottom by the moſt Eagle-eyed of the Parliament, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be found contrary to the Miniſters proteſtation, that they were no wayes the cauſe of the peoples convening or fighting at Mauchlin.</p>
            <p>The paralell that the Warner makes betwixt the generall aſſembly and Parliament is malicious in all its parts.
<note place="margin">The aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> For the firſt, though the one Court be civill, and the other Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, yet the Presbyterians lay the authority of both upon a divine fundation, that for conſcience ſake the Courts civil muſt be obeyed in all their Lawfull commands, alſewell as the aſſemblyes of the Church; God being the author of the politick order as well as the Eccleſiaſtick, and the revenger of the contempt of the one alswell as of the other. But what doth the Warner meane, to mock at Miniſters for carrying themſelves as the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, for judging accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of Scripture, for caring for life eternall? is he become ſo shamefullie impious, as to perſwade Miniſters to give over the care of life eternall, to lay aſide the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and deny their ambaſſage from Jeſus Chriſt? behold what Spirit leads our praelats, while they jeere the World out of all Religion, and chaſe away Miniſters from Chriſt, from Scripture, from eternall life.</p>
            <p>Of the ſecond part of the parallell, that people are more ready to obey their Miniſters then their Magiſtrats what shall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52046:38"/>be made? all the power which Miniſters have with the people is builded on their love to God and religion: how much ſo ever it is, a good Statseman will not envy it: for he knowes that God and conſcience conſtraine Miniſters to imploy all the power they have with the people to the good of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat, as the deputy and ſervant of God for the peoples true good. The Warner heer underſtands beſt his owne meaning, while he ſcoffes at Miniſters for their threatning of men with hells fire. Are our Praelats come to ſuch open proclamations of their Atheiſme, as to printe their deſires to banish out of the hearts of people all feare not only of Church-cenſures, but even of hell it ſelfe? whither may not Satan drive at laſt the inſtruments of his Kingdome?</p>
            <p>The third parte of the paralell conſiſts of a number of unjuſt and falſe imputations before particularly refuted.</p>
            <p>What he ſubjoines of the power of the generall Aſſembly to name Comittees to ſit in the intervalls of Aſſemblies,
<note place="margin">The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of comit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees is a right of every court as well Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick as civil.</note> it is but a poore charge: is it not the dayly practiſe of the Parliaments of Scotland to nominat their Comittees of State for the intervalls of Parliament? Is it not ane inhaerent right to every Court to name ſome of their number to cognoſce upon things within their owne ſpheare at what ever times the court it ſelfe finds expedient; how ever the judicatories of the Church by the lawes of the Kingdome being authorized to meet when themſelves think fit both ordinarly and <hi>pro re nata,</hi> their power of appointing Comittees for their owne affaires was never queſtioned: and truely theſe Comittees in the times of our late troubles when many were lying in waite to diſturbe both Church and State, have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to meet oftner then otherwiſe any of their members did deſire: whoſe diverſion from their particular charges (though for attendance on the publick) is joyned with ſo great fashery and expence, that with all their heart they could
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52046:38"/>be glade to decline it, if feare of detriment to the Church made not theſe meetings very neceſſary.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Presbytery is no burden to any honeſt man.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE bounds and compaſſe of the Warners rage againſt the Presbytery is very large;
<note place="margin">There is no rigour at all in the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</note> not being content to have incenſed the King and Parliament againſt it, he comes downe to the body of the people, and will have them beleeve the ſpeciall enimity of the Scots diſcipline againſt them, firſt becauſe it inflicts Church cenſures upon every one for the ſmalleſt faults. Anſ. The faults which the Warner men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may well be ane occaſion of a private advice in the eare, but that any of them did ever procure the ſmalleſt cenſure of the Church, it is a great untruth: no man who knowes us will complaine of our rigour, heerwe wish we were able to refute upon as good reaſon the charge of our ſlaknes in the mouth of ſectaries as we are that of our ſtrictnes in the mouth of Eraſtianes. Wee would know of the Warner, what are theſe Sabbath recreations, which he ſaith are void of ſcandal, and conſiſtent with the dutyes of the day; are they not the ſtage playes and the other honeſt paſtimes, wherewith his friends were wonte to ſanctify the Lords day, as no more a Sabbath then any other day in the yeare, and much leſſe then diverſe popish feſtivalls? An Apoſteme in the loweſt gutt will shew it ſelfe by the unſavory vapours, which now and then are eructat from it. That ever in Scotland there was one word of debate about ſtarch and cuffs, is more then the Warner can prove.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:52046:39"/>
            <p> The ſecond oppreſſion,
<note place="margin">Crimes till repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of ought to keep from the holy table.</note> whereby the Presbytery trods the people under foot is a rare cruelty; that perſons, for grievous crimes whereof the Magiſtrate takes notice, are called to Eccleſiaſtick repentance. Will the Doctor in his fury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, run out upon all his owne friends for no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a fault? Will either the English or popish praelats admit murtherers, whoores or theeves to the holy table without any ſignes of repentance? Is not the greateſt crime the ground of the greateſt ſcandal? Shall ſmall ſcandals be purged away by repentance, and the greateſt be totally paſt by? The Doctor heer may know his owne meaning but others will confeſſe their ignorance of his minde.</p>
            <p>The third grievance he would have the people conceive againſt the Presbytery is,
<note place="margin">Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Scotland is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to any.</note> the rigour of their excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in this alſo the Warner ſeemes to know little of the Scots way, let excommunication be ſo ſeveer in Scotland as is poſſible, yet the hurt of it is but ſmall: it is ſo rare an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, men may live long in Scotland, and al their life never ſee that cenſure execute; I have lived in one of the greateſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that land and for fourty ſeven yeares even from my birth to this day, that cenſure to my knowledge or hearing was never execute there in my dayes but twice; firſt upon ane obſtinat and very profaine Papiſt; and nixt on ſome hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſcandalous praelats. Againe when any is excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the Church, we goe no further with them then Pauls commande: 2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.14. only they who are not tyed to them by naturall bonds, abſtaine from familiar and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary converſation, to bring them by the ſence of this shame to repentance for their fins.</p>
            <p>Thirdly the civil inconvenientes which followe that cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure come along from the State and the acts of Parliament, for which the Church ought not to be challenged; eſpecially by praelats who wont to allow their officials to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52046:39"/>whole incorporations of people for a ſmall debt of mony, and to preſſe the contemners of that frivolous and profane ſentence, with all the civil inconvenientes they could. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what ever be the laws in Scotland againſt them who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues long in the contempt of Excommunication, (which are not inflicted but for great ſins and after a long proceſſe) yet certainly their execution is very farre from all cruelty, as they who know the proceedings of that land, will beare witnes.</p>
            <p>What he objects about fugitives; it is true, when a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is begunne, a fugitive may have it concluded, and ſent after him; but we count not that man a fugitive from diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline or contumacious as the Warner quarrels us, who upon juſt feare to hazard his life does not compear.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Preſbytery is hurtfull to no order of men.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>PRaelaticall malice is exorbitant beyond the bounds of all shew of moderation:
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Presbytery</note> was it not enough to have calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat the Presbytery to Kings, Princes and Soveraignes, to Parliaments and all Courts of Juſtice, to people and all particular perſons, but yet a new chapter muſt be made to shew in it the hurtfullnes of Presbytery to all orders of men: wee muſt have patience to ſtand a little in the unſavoury aire of this vomite alſo.
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats were conſtant oppreſſors: of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and gentry.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Unto the nobility and gentry the Presbitery muſt be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe it ſubjecteth them to the cenſures of a raw hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy novice and a few ignorant artificers. Anſ. Its good that our praelats are now turned pleaders againſt the oppreſſion
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52046:40"/>of the Nobility and gentry: its not long ſince the praelatical clergy were accuſtomed to ſet their ſoule feet on the necks of the greateſt peeres of the three Kingdomes with to high a pride and preſſure; that to shake of their yock, no ſuffering, no hazard has been refuſed by the beſt of the Nobility and gentry of <hi>Britaine:</hi> but natures and principles are ſo eaſy to be changed, that no man now needs feare any more oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the praelats, though they were ſet downe again and wel warned in their repaired throns.</p>
            <p>But to the challenge we anſwer,
<note place="margin">The way of the Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that of the Engliſh E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy.</note> that the meaneſt Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of a ſmall Congregation in Scotland conſiſts of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and a dozen (at leaſt) of the moſt wiſe pious and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that are to be found in the whole flock; which yet the Warner heer makes to be judges but of the common people in matters of ſmalleſt moment. But for the claſſicall Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, to which he referres the Eccleſiaſticall cauſes of the Nobility and gentry, and before whom indeed every Church proceſſe of any conſiderable weight or difficulty does come, though it concerne the perſons of the meaneſt of the people, this Presbytery does conſiſt ordinarly of fifeteen Miniſters (at leaſt) and fifeteen of the moſt qualified noblemen, gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemen and Burgeſſes, which the circuit of fifteen parishes can affoord, theſe (I hope) may make up a judicatory of a great deale more worth then any officiall court, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts but of one judge, a petty mercenary lawyer, to whoſe care alone the whole Eccleſiaſtick juriſdiction over all the Nobility and gentry of diverſe shyres is committed, and that without appeale as the Warner has told us, except it be to a Court of delegats; a miſerable releefe that all the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, gentry and Commons of a Kingdome, who are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Epiſcopall officials, have no other remedie but to goe attende a Committee of two or three civilians at London deputed for the diſcuſſing of ſuch appeales.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:52046:40"/>
            <p> The Presbyterian courſe is much more ready, ſolide and equitable: if any grievance ariſe from the ſentence of a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, a Synode twice a yeare doth ſit in the bounds, and attends for a week, or if need be, longer, to determine all appeales, and redreſſe all grievances: now the Synode does conſiſt of all the Miniſters within the bounds, which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narly are of diverſe whole shyres as that of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> of the upper and neather ward of <hi>Clidſedaile, Baerranfrow, Lennox, Kile, Carrick</hi> and <hi>Cunninghame;</hi> alſo beſide Miniſters, the conſtant members who have deciſive voice in Synodes, are the chiefe Noblemen, Gentlemen and Burgeſſes of all theſe shyres, among whom their be ſuch parts for judgment as are not to be found nor expected in any inferiour civil Court of the Kingdom, yet if it fall out ſo, that any party be grieved with the ſentence of a Synode, there is then a farther and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appeale in a Generall aſſembly, which conſiſts of as many Burgeſſes and more Gentlemen from every shire of the Kingdome then come to any Parliament: beſide the prime Nobility and choiſeſt Miniſtry of the land; having the Kings Majeſtie in perſone, or in his abſence, his high Commiſſioner to be their praeſident. This meeting yeerly (or oftner, if need be) ſits ordinarly a month; and if they think fit, longer: the number, the wiſedome, the eminency of the members of this Court is ſo great, that beſide the unjuſtice, it were a very needleſſe labour to appeal from it to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for (as we have ſaid) the King or his high Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſits in both meetings albeit in a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t capacity: the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and qualification of knights and Burgeſſes is ever large as great in the aſſembly as in the Parliament: only the difference is, that in the Parliament all the Nobility in the Kingdom ſit without any election and by virtue of their birth, but in the Aſſembly only who for age, wiſedome and piety are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the Presbyteries as fitteſt to judge in Eccleſiaſtick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52046:41"/>but to make up this oddes of the abſence of ſome Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Aſſembly is alwayes adorned with above ane hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the choifeſt Paſtors of the whole land, none whereof may ſit in Parliament: nothing that can conciliate authority to a Court, or can be found in the Nation, is wanting to the generall aſſembly; how baſely ſo ever our praelats are pleaſed to trample upon it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond alledged hurt which the Nobility have from the Presbytery,
<note place="margin">All queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Scotland are now ended.</note> is the loſſe of their patronages by congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations electing their Paſtors. Anſ. Howſoever the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Church about patronages is no other then that of the Reformed divines abroad, yet have our Presbyteries alwayes with patience endured patrons to preſent unto va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Churches, till the Parliament now at laſt hath taken away that grievance.</p>
            <p>The Nobilities laſt hurt by the Presbytry is their loſſe of all their impropriations and Abey-lands.
<note place="margin">The poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of Church lands were ever feared for Bishops, but never for the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</note> Anſ. How Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophantick an accuſation is this? for who knowes not, how farre the whole generation of the praelaticke faction doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the higheſt of the Presbyterians in zeale againſt that which they call Sacriledge? never any of the Presbyterians did attempt either by violence, or a courſe of Law, to put out any of the Nobility or gentry from their poſſeſſions of the Church-lands, but very lately the threats and vigorous activity of the praelats, and their followers were ſo vehement in this kinde, that all the Nobility and gentry who had any intereſt, were wackned (to purpoſe) to take heed of their rights. In the laſt Parliament of Scotland when the power of the Church was as great as they expect to ſee it againe, though they obtained the abolition of patronages, yet were the poſſeſſors of the Church-lands and tythes ſo little har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that their rights therto were more cleerly and ſtrongly confirmed, then by any praeceding Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:52046:41"/>
            <p> The fourth hurt is that every ordinary Presbyter wil make himſelfe a Noblemans fellow. Anſ. No where in the World does gracious Miniſters (though meane borne men) receive more reſpect from the Nobility then in Scotland: neither any where does the Nobility and gentry receive more duely their honour then from the Miniſters there. That inſolent ſpeach fathered on Mr. <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> is demonſtrat to be a fabulous calumny in the hiſtoricall vindication.</p>
            <p>However the Warner may know that in all Europe where Bishops have place, it hes ever, (at leaſt theſe 800 yeares) been their nature to trample under foot the higheſt of the Nobility. As the Pope muſt be above the Emperour, ſo a little Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> can tell to King <hi>Iames,</hi> that hee may well be counted a companion of any Ilander King: were the Bishops in Scotland ever content, till they got in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the right hand and the neareſt ſeates to the throne, and the doore of the greateſt Earles, Marqueſſes and duks? was it not Epiſcopacy, that did advance poore and capricious pedants to ſtrive for the whyte ſtaves &amp; great Seales of both Kingdomes, with the prime Nobility; and often overcome them in that ſtrife? In Scotland I know, and the Warner will aſſure for England and Ireland, that the baſeſt borne of his brethren hes ruff led it in the ſecreet counſel, in the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Exchequer, in the higheſt courts of juſtice, with the greateſt Lords of the Land: its not ſo long, that yet it can be forgotten,
<note place="margin">The prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null the being of al the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for their want of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.</note> ſince a Bishop of <hi>Galloway</hi> had the modeſty to give unto a Marquiſe of <hi>Argile,</hi> tanta mont to a broadly in his face at the counſel table. The Warner shall doe well to reckon no more with Presbyters for braving of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>The nixt hee will have to bee wronged by the Presbytery are the orthodoxe clergy. Anſ. All the Presbyterians to him (it ſeemes) are heterodoxe; Epiſcopacy is ſo neceſſary
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52046:42"/>a truth that who denies it, muſt be ſtamped as for a grievous errour with the character of heterodox. The following words cleere this to be his mind, <hi>they loſſe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the confortable aſſurance of undoubted ſucceſſion by Epiſcopall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination:</hi> what ſence can be made of theſe words, but that all Miniſters who are not ordained by Bishops, muſt lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the confortleſſe uncertainty of any lawfull ſucceſſion in their miniſteriall charge, for want of this ſucceſſion through the lineall deſcent of Bishops from the Apoſtles; at leaſt for want of ordination by the hands of Bishops, as if unto them only the power of miſſion and ordination to the Miniſtry were committed by Chriſt: becauſe of this defect the Presbyterian Miniſters muſt not only want the confort of an aſſured and undoubted calling to the Miniſtry, but may very well know and be aſſured that their calling and Miniſtry is null. The words immediatly following are ſcraped out after their printing: for what cauſe the author leſt knoweth: but the purpoſe in hand makes it proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the deletted words did expreſſe more of his mind, then it was ſafe in this time and place to ſpeake out: it was the late doctrine of <hi>Doctor Brambles</hi> prime friends, that the want of Epiſcopall ordination did not only annull the calling of all the Miniſters of <hi>France, Holland, Zwit-zerland,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> but alſo did hinder all theſe ſocieties to be true Churches: for that popular Sophiſme of the Jeſuits our prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats did greedily ſwallow; where are no true Sacraments, there is no true Church; and where is no true Miniſtry, there are no true Sacraments; and where no true ordination, there is no true miniſtry; and where no Bishops, there is no true ordination: and ſo in no reformed country but in England and Ireland where were true Bishops, is any true Church. When Epiſcopacy comes to this height of elevation, that the want of it muſt annuall the Miniſtry, yea null the Church and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52046:42"/>all the Reformed at one ſtrock, is it any mervaill, that all of them doe concurre together for their own preſervation, to abolish this inſolent abaddon and deſtroyer? and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all its ruine have yet no diſconfort at all, nor any the leaſt doubt of their moſt lawfull ordination by the hands of the Presbytry.</p>
            <p>After all this was writen, is heer it ſtands,
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats are ſo baſelie injurious to all the reformed Churches that their ſelfes are aſhamed of it.</note> another copie of the Warners book was brought to my hand wherin <hi>I found the deleted line ſtand printed in theſe diſtinct tearmes, and put it to a dangerous queſtion whither it be within the payle of the Church,</hi> the deciphering of theſe words puts it beyond all peradventure that what I did conjecture of the Warner and his Brethrens minde, of the ſtate of all the reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, was no mis-take, but that they doe truely judge the want of Epiſcopall ordination to exclude all the Miniſters of other Reformed Churches, and their flocks alſo from the lines of the true Church. This indeed is a moſt dangerous queſtion: for it ſtricks at the root of all. If the Warner out of remorſe of conſcience had blotted out of his book that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, the repentance had been commendable: But he hes left ſo much yet behind unſcraped out, as does shew his minde to continue what it was, ſo that feare alone to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the reformed heere at this unſeaſonable time, ſeemes to have been the cauſe of deleting theſe too cleare expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the praelaticall tenet againſt the very being and ſubſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of all the Proteſtant Churches, which want Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe ſtill ſtand upon the extreame pinacle of impudency and arrogance, denying the Reformed to be true Churches, and without ſcuple averring Rome as shee ſtands this day, under the counſel of Trent, to be a Church moſt true, wherin there is an eaſy way of ſalvation, from which all ſeparation is needleſſe, and with which a re-uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were much to be deſired? That gracious faction this day
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52046:43"/>is willing enough to perſwade, or at leaſt to reſt content without any oppoſition that the King should of himſelfe without and before a Parliament, (though contrary to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtanding Lawes) grant under his hand and ſeale a full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Religion to the bloody Irish, and to put in their hands, both armes, Caſtles and prime Places of truſt in the State; that the King should give aſſurance of his endeavour, to get all theſe ratified in the nixt Parliament of England, theſe men can heare with all moderation and patience: but behold their furious impatience, their whole art and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is wakned, when they heare of any appearance of the Kings inclination towards covenanting Proteſtants: night and day they beate in his Majeſties head, that all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieves of the world does lurke in that miſerable covenant, that death and any misfortune, that the ruine of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ought much rather to bee imbraced by his Majeſtie, then that prodigious Monſter, that very hell of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, becauſe forſooth it doth oblige in plane tearmes the taker to endeavour (in his ſtation) the abolition of their great Goddeſſe, praelacy.</p>
            <p>The nixt hurt of Miniſters from the Presbytry,
<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy have ever been covered with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, and contempt.</note> is, that by it they are brought to ignorance, contempt and beggery. Anſ. Whither Epiſcopacy or Presbytry is the fitteſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to avert theſe evills, let reaſon or experience teach men to judge. The Presbyteriall diſcipline doth oblige to a great deale of ſeverer tryalls in all ſort of learning requiſite in a divine before ordination then doth the Epiſcopall: let either the rule or practiſe of Presbyterian and Epiſcopall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination be compared or the weekly Exerciſes and monthly diſputations in Latine upon the controverted heads be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon which the Presbytry exacts of every Miniſter after his ordination all the dayes of his life: for experience let the <hi>French, Dutch</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> divines who have been or yet are,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52046:43"/>be compared with the ordinary generation of the English Clergie, and it will be found, that the praelats have not great reaſon ſo ſuperciliouſly to look downe with contempt upon their Brethrens learning. I hope, <hi>Cartwright, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker, Perkins, Reynolds, Parker, Ames,</hi> and other Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian English were inferior in learning to none of their oppoſits: ſome of the English Bishops has not wanted good ſtore of learning, but the moſt of them (I beleeve) wilbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leave of boaſting in this ſubject, what does the Warner ſpeake to us of ignorance, contempt and Beggery? does not all the world know, that albeit ſome few, ſcarce one of twenty, did brook good benefices, yea plurality of them whereby to live in ſplendor at Court, or where they liſted in their non-reſidency, nevertheleſſe it hath been much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that the greateſt parte of the prieſts, who had the cure of ſoules thorow all the Kingdome of England, were incomparably the moſt ignorant, beggerly and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible clergy, that ever have been ſeen in any of the reformed Churches? neither did we ever heare of any great ſtudy in the Praelats to remeed theſe evils, albeit ſome of them be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident enough for their owne families. <hi>Doctor Bramble</hi> knowes who had the skill before they had ſitten ſeven yeare in their charge to purchaſe above fifeteen hundred pounds a yeare for themſelves and their heirs what ſomever.</p>
            <p>The third evil which the Ptesbytery brings upon Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is that it makes them prat and pray nonſence everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. Anſ.
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to hate preaching and prayer but to ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</note> It is indeed a great heartbrake unto igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, lazy and unconſciencious Miniſters to be put to the paines of preaching and prayer, when a read ſervice was wont to be all their exerciſe: but we thought that all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ingenuous men had long agoe been put from ſuch impudence. It was the late labour of the praelats by all their skill to diſgrace preaching and praying without booke, to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52046:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:52046:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:52046:45"/>cry up the Liturgy as the only ſervice of God, and to idolize it as a moſt heavenly and divine peece of write, which yet is nought but a tranſcript of the ſuperſtitious breviary and idolatrous miſſall of Rome. The Warner would doe well to conſider and anſwer after ſeven yeares adviſement Mr. <hi>Bailie</hi> his pararell of the ſervice with the miſſall and Breviarie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee preſente the world with new paralels of the English liturgy, with the directories of the Reformed Churches. Is it ſo indeed, that all preaching and praying without book is but a pratting of non-ſence everlaſtingly, why then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues the King and many well minded men to be deceived by our Doctors, while they affirme that they are as much for preaching in their practiſe and opinion as the Presbyterians, and for prayer without book alſo, before and after ſermon, and in many other occaſions? it ſeemes theſe affirmations are nothing but groſſe diſſimulation in this time of their low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and affliction, to decline the envy of people againſt them for their profane contempt of divine ordinances; for wee may ſee heere their tenet to remaine what it was, and themſelves ready enough, when their ſeaſon shall be fitter, to ring it out loud in the eares of the World, that for divine ſervice people needs no more but the reading of the liturgy,
<note place="margin">Vide la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ium. cap. 7.</note> that ſermons on week dayes and Sundayes afternoon muſt all be laid aſide, that on the Sabbath before noone Sermon is needleſſe, and from the mouths of the moſt Preachers very noxious; that when ſome learned Schollars are pleaſed on ſome feſtivall dayes to have an oration, it would be short and and according to the Court paterne, without all Spirit and life for edification; but by all meanes it muſt bee provided, that no word of prayer either before or after be ſpoken, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only a bidding to pray, for many things even for the welfare of the ſoules departed; and all this alone in the words of the Lords prayer. If any shall dare to expreſſe the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52046:45"/>deſires of his heart to God in privat or publick in any words of his own framing hee is a groſſe Puritan, who is bold to offer to God his own nonſence rather then the auncient; and well adviſed prayers of the holy Church.</p>
            <p>The Warner is heer alſo miſtaken in his beleefe, that ever the Church of Scotland had any Liturgy, they had and have ſtill ſome formes for helpe and direction, but no ty ever in any of them by law or practiſe: they doe not condemne the uſe of ſet formes for rules, yea nor for uſe in beginners, who are thereby endeavouring to attaine a readineſſe to pray in their family out of their owne heart in the words which Gods ſpirit dytes to them; but for Miniſters to ſuppreſſe their moſt confortable and uſefull gift of prayer by tying their mouth unto ſuch formes which themſelves or others have compoſed wee count it a wrong to the giver, and to him who has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the gift, and to the gift, and to the Church for whoſe uſe that was beſtowed.</p>
            <p>In the nixt place the Warner makes the Presbytry injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to parents,
<note place="margin">Epiſcopall warrants for clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtin mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, rob Parents of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> by marying their children contrary to their conſent, and forcing them to give to the disobedient as large a portion as to any other of their obedient children, and that it is no mervail the Scots should doe theſe things who have ſtripped the King the father of their country of his juſt rights. Anſ. By the Warners rule all the actions of a nation where a Presbytry lodges muſt be charged on the back of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytry. II. The Parliament of Scotland denyes, that they have ſtripped the King of his juſt rights; while he was ſtirred up and keeped on by the praelaticall faction to courſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to himſelfe and all his people; after the shedding of much blood, before the exerciſe of all parts of his royall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they only required for all ſatisfaction and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to religion and liberties, the grant of ſome few moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable demands. The unhappy Praelats from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52046:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>of our troubles to this day finding our great demande to runne upon the abolition of their office, did ever preſſe his Majeſtie to deny us that ſatisfaction, and rather then Bishops should be laid aſide they have concluded that the King himſelfe, and all his family and all his three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes shall perish: yet with all patience the Scotes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to ſupplicat and to offer not only their Kingdome, but their lives and eſtats and all they have for his Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice upon the grant of their few and eaſy demands; but no miſery either of King or people can overcome the deſperat obſtinacy of Praelaticall hearts.</p>
            <p>As for parents conſent to the mariage of their children, how tenderly it is provided for in Scotland it may be ſeen at length in the very place cited. It was the Bishops, who by their warrants for clandeſtine mariages, and diſpenſations with mariages without warrant have ſpoiled many parents of their deare children: with ſuch abhominations the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery was never acquainted; all that is alleadged out of that place of our diſcipline is, when a cruel parent or tutor abuſes their authority over their children, and againſt all reaſon for their owne evill ends perverſely will croſſe their children in their lawfull and every way honeſt deſires of mariage; that in that caſe the Magiſtrats and Miniſters may be intreated by the grieved childe to deale with the unjuſt parent or tutor, that by their mediation reaſon may be done. I beleeve this advice is ſo full of equity, that no Church nor State in the world will complaine of it: but how ever it be, this caſe is ſo rare in Scotland that I profeſſe, I never in my life did know, nor did heare of any child before my dayes, who did aſſay by the authoritative ſentence of a Magiſtrate or Miniſter to force their parents conſent to their marriage. As for the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners addition of the Miniſters compelling parents to give portions to their children, that the Church of Scotland haths
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52046:46"/>any ſuch canon or practiſe its an impudent lie, but in the place alledged is a paſſage againſt the ſparing of the life of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, contrary to the Law of God: and for the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Adulterers, when by the negligence of the Magiſtrat their life is ſpared, this poſſibly may be the thorne in the ſide of ſome which makes them bite and ſpurne with the heele ſo furiouſly againſt the Authors and lovers of ſo ſevere a diſcipline.</p>
            <p>The Presbyteries nixt injury is done to the Lawyers, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes &amp; other Eccleſiaſtick Courts revoke their Sentences. Anſ. No ſuch matter ever was attempted in Scotland; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent prohibitions have been obtained by curtiſan Bishops, againſt the higheſt civil judicatories in England, but that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Presbitry or Synode in Scotland did ſo much as aſſay to impede or repeale the proceedings of any the meaneſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil court, I did never heare it ſo much as alleaged by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</p>
            <p>The nixt injury is againſt all Maſters,
<note place="margin">Serious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing is no Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal crime.</note> and Miſtreſſes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, whom the Presbytery will have to be perſonally exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in their knowledge once a yeare, and to be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat, if groſly and wilfully ignorant. Anſ. If it bee a crime for a Miniſter to call together parcels of his congre ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be inſtructed in the grounds of Religion, that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and children and (where ignorance is ſuſpected,) others alſo may be tryed in their knowledge of the Catechiſme; or if it bee a crime that in family-viſitations oftener then once a yeare the converſation of every member of the Church may be looked upon; we confeſſe the Miniſters of Scotland were guilty thereof, and ſo farre as we know the generality of the Epiſcopall faction may purge themſelves by oath of any ſuch imputation: for they had ſomewhat elſe to doe, then to be at the pains of inſtructing or trying the Spirituall State of every sheep in their flocks: we confeſſe likewiſe, that it is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52046:47"/>both our order and practiſe to keep off from the holy table, whom wee find groſlly and wilfully ignorant: but that ever any for ſimple ignorance was excommunicat in Scotland, none who knowes us will affirme it.</p>
            <p>The laſt whom he will have to be wronged by the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery are the common people,
<note place="margin">Church feſſions are not high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiones.</note> who muſt groane under a high commiſſion in every parish, where ignorant governors rule all without Law, medling even in domeſticall jarres be twixt man and wife, Maſter and Servant. Anſ. This is but a gybe of revenge for the overthrow of their Tyrannous high Commiſſion-Court, where they were wont to play the Rex at their pleaſure above the higheſt ſubjects of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and would never give over that their inſolent dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering court, till the King and Parliaments of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes did agree to throw it down about their eares. The thing he jeares at, is the congregation all Eldership, a judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory which all the Reformed doe enjoy to their great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort as much as Scotland. They are farre from all arbitrary judications; their Lawes are the holy Scripture and acts of ſuperior Church-judicatories, which rule ſo clearly the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their cogniſance, that rarely any difficulty remaines therein: or if it doe, immediatly by reference or appeal it is tranſmitted to the Claſſes or Synode. The judges in the loweſt Eldership (as wee have ſaid before) are a doſzen at leaſt, of the moſt able and pious who can bee hade in a whole congregation to joine with the Paſtors one or more as they fall to be: but the Epiſcopall way is to have no diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline at all in any congregation: only where there is hope of a fyne, the Bishops officiall will ſummon before his owne learned and conſcientious wiſedome, who ever within the whole dioces have fallen into ſuch a fault as hee pleaſeth to take notice of: as for domeſtick infirmities, Presbyterians are moſt tender to medle therein; they come never before
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52046:47"/>any judicatory, but both where the fault is great, and the ſcandal thereof flagrant, and broken out beyond the wals of the family.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the great injuries and hurts which the Church diſcipline has procured to all orders of men in the whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed world, when Epiſcopacy has been ſuch an innocent lambe, or rather ſo holy an angel upon earth, that no harme at all has ever come by it to any mortall creature: a misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving Jew will nothing misdoubt this ſo evident a truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. ULT.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Warners exceptions againſt the covenant are full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence but exceeding frivolous.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THough in the former Chapters the Warner has shewed out more venome and gall then the bagge of any one mans ſtomack could have been ſuppoſed capable of, yet as if he were but beginning to vomite, in this laſt Chapter of the covenant a new flood of blacker poyſon rusheth out of his pen. His undertaking is great, to demonſtrat cleerly that the covenant is meerly void wicked and impious. His firſt clear demonſtration is, that it was deviſed by ſtrangers, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by ſubjects, who wanted requiſite power, and was extorted by juſt feare of unjuſt ſuffering, ſo that many that took it with their lips, never conſented with their hearts. Anſ. This cleer demonſtration is but a poor and evill argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the Major, if it were put in forme, would hardly be granted,
<note place="margin">The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was not diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to union.</note> but I ſtand on the minor as weake and falſe for the covenant was not deviſed by ſtrangers, the Commiſſioners of the Parliament of England together with the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Parliament and generall aſſembly of Scotland
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52046:48"/>were the firſt and only framers thereof, but they who gave the life and being to it in England were the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament at Weſt-Miniſter by the Kings call, and at that time acknowledged by his Majeſtie without any queſtion about the lawfullnes of their conſtitution and authority: theſe men and that Court were not I hope great ſtrangers in England. The covenant was not impoſed upon the King: but the Parliaments of both Kingdomes made it their earneſt deſire unto his Majeſtie, that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to joyne with them in that Covenant, which they did judge to be a maine peece of their ſecurity for their Religion and liberties in all the three Kingdomes. As for their impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it upon the ſubjects of England, an ordinance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (though the King conſent not) by the uncontrover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lawes of England, is a ſufficient authority to crave obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of all the ſubjects of England, during the continuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of that Parliament.</p>
            <p>The laſt part of the demonſtration is dishonorable indeed to the English Nation if it were true, it was no dishonour to England to joyne with their brethren of Scotland in a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for mantainance of their Religion and Liberties: but for many of the English to ſweare a covenant with their lippes, from which their heart did diſſent and upon this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of heart and mouth to plead the nullity of the oath, and to advance this plea ſo high as to a cleer demonſtration, this is ſuch a dishonour and dishoneſty, that a greater can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fall upon a man of reputed integrity, Eſpecially when the ground of the lie and perjury is an evident falshood: for the covenant was not extorted from any flesh in England by feare of any unjuſt ſuffering; ſo far was it from this, that to this day it could never be obtained from the Parliament of England, to enjoyne that covenant upon any by the penul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a two pence.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:52046:48"/>
            <p> The Warners ſecond demonſtration is no better then the firſt, the ground of it is,
<note place="margin">Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what they ſweare.</note> that all oathes are void which have deceipt and errour of the ſubſtantiall conditions incident to them. This ground had need to be much better cautioned, then heere it is, before it can ſtand for a major of a clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration: but how is the minor proved? behold how much short the Warners proofes are of his great boaſtings. His firſt argument is grounded upon an evident falshood, that in the Covenant we ſweare the lately deviſed diſcipline to be Chriſts inſtitution. Anſ. There is no ſuch word nor any ſuch matter in all the Covenant: was the Warners ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ſo great againſt that peece of write, that being to make cleare demonſtrations againſt it, hee would not ſo much as caſt his eye upon that which he was to oppugne, Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſweare to endeavour the reformation of England, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God and the beſt reformed Churches, but not a word of the Scotes Presbytery, nor of any thing in any Church even the beſt reformed, unleſſe it be found ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the paterne of Gods holy word.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ground of his demonſtrantion is alſo an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent errour,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner unwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly comends the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> that the covenant in hand is one and the ſame with that of King <hi>Iames.</hi> Anſ. Such a fancy came never in the head of any man, I know; much leſſe was it ever wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or ſpoken by any: that the Covenant of King <hi>Iames</hi> in Scotland 1580, should bee one and the ſame with the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of all the three Kingdomes 1643, whatſoever iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities may appeare in the matter and ſimilitude, in the ends of both; but the groſſeſt errors are ſolide enough grounds for praelaticall clear demonſtrations. Yet heere the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner underſtands not how hee is cutting his own vines; his friends in Scotland will give him ſmall thanks for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing unto the nationall Covenant of Scotland, (that Covenant of King <hi>Iames</hi>) theſe three properties, that it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52046:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:52046:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:52046:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>was iſſued out by the Kings authority, that it was for the maintenance of the Lawes of the realme, and for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the eſtablished Religion: tyme brings adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to confeſſe of their own accord long denyed truthes. But the Characters, which the Warner inprints upon the ſolemne league and Covenant of the three Kingdomes, wee muſt bee pardoned to controvert, till he have taken ſome leaſure to trie his wilde aſſertions. Firſt that the league is againſt the authority of the King, ſecondly that it is againſt the Law; and thirdly that it is for the overthrow of Religion. The man cannot think, that any should beleeve his dictats of this kind without proofe, ſince the expreſſe words of that league do flatly contradict him in all theſe three poſitions.</p>
            <p>His gentle memento, that Scotland, when they ſued for aid from the crowne of England, had not the English diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline obtruded upon their Church, might heer have been ſpaired: was not the English diſcipline and liturgy obtruded upon us by the praelats of England with all craft and force? did we ever obtrude our diſciplin upon the English? but when they of their owne free and long deliberate choice had abolished Bishops and promiſed to ſet up Presbytery, ſo far as they had found it agreable to the word of God, were wee not in all reaſon obliged to encourage and aſſiſt them in ſo pious a work?</p>
            <p>In the nixt words the Warner for all his great boaſts fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the weaknes of all the former grounds of his ſeconde demonſtration,
<note place="margin">The King did not clame the ſole and abſolute poſſeſſion of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia.</note> he offers three new ones: which doubtles will doe the deid: for he avowes poſitively that his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing grounds are demonſtrative, yet whoſoever shalbe pleaſed to grip them with never ſo ſoft an hand shall find them all to be but vanity and wind. The firſt, after a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of proſyllogiſmes reſts upon theſe two foundations, firſt that the right of the <hi>militia</hi> reſides in the King alone: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:52046:50"/>that by the covenant the <hi>militia</hi> is taken out of the Kings hands; and that every covenanter by his covenant diſpoſes of himſelfe and of his armes, againſt the right which the King hath into him. Anſ. The Warner will have much adoe to prove this ſecond ſo, that it may be a ground of a clear demonſtration: but for the firſt that the power of the <hi>militia</hi> of England doth reſide in the King alone, that the two houſes of Parliament have nothing at all to doe with it, and that their taking of armes for the defence of the liberties of England or any other imaginable cauſe againſt any party countenanced by the Kings preſence againſt his lawes muſt be altogether unlawfull; if his demonſtration be no clearer, then the ground where upon he builds it, I am ſure, it will not be viſible to any of his oppofits: who are not like to be convinced of open rebellion by his naked aſſertion, upon which alone he layes this his mighty ground. Beleeve it, he had need to aſſay its releefe with ſome colour of ane argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for none of his owne friends will now take it of his hand for ane indemonſtrable principle, ſince the King for a long time was willing to acknowledge the Parliaments jointe intereſt in the <hi>militia,</hi> yea to put the whole <hi>militia</hi> in their hands alone for a good number of yeares to come: ſo farre was his Majeſtie from the thoughts, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments medling with a parte of the militia, in the time of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident dangers, should be ſo certainly and clearly the crime of rebellion.</p>
            <p>The Warners ſecond demonſtrative ground wee admit without queſtion in the major, that where the matter is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently unlawfull, the oath is not binding; but the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this in the minor is very falſe. All that hee brings to make it appeare to be true, is that the King is the ſupreame Legiſlator, that it is unlawfull for the ſubjects of England to change any thing eſtablished by Law, eſpecially to the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:52046:51"/>prejudice of the Praelats without their own conſent, they being a third order of the Kingdom; otherwiſe it would be a harder meaſure then the Friers and Abbots received from <hi>Henry</hi> the eight.
<note place="margin">The change of lawes in England ordinarly beginne by the two houſes without the King.</note> Anſ. May the Warner be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how farre his dictats heere are from all reaſon, much more from evident demonſtrations. That the burden of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and ceremonies was become ſo heavy to all the three Kingdomes, that there was reaſon to endeavour their lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide, he does not offer to diſpute; but all his complanit runnes againſt the manner of their removall: this (ſay I) was done in no other then the ordinary and high path-way, whereby all burdenſome Lawes and cuſtomes uſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. Doth not the Houſes of Parliament firſt begin with their ordinance before the Kings conſent be ſought to a Law? is not an ordinance of the Lords and Commons a good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to change a former Law during the ſitting of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The Lawes and cuſtomes of England permit not the King by his diſſent to ſtoppe that change.
<note place="margin">The King did really conſent to the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bishops.</note> I grant for the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an ordinance to a ſtanding Law, the Kings conſent is required, but with what qualifications and exceptions wee need not heere to debate, ſince his Majeſties conſent to the preſent caſe of abolishing Bishops was obtained well neere as farre as was deſired; and what is yet lacking, wee are in a faire way to obtaine it: for the Kings Majeſtie long agoe did agree to the rooting out of Epiſcopacy in Scotland, he was willing alſo in England and Ireland to put them out of the Parliament, and all civil courts, and to diveſt them of all civil power, and to joyne with them Presbyteries for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and ſpirituall juriſdiction; yea to abolish them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally name and thing, not only for three yeares but ever till he and his Parliament should agree upon ſome ſetled order for the Church, was not this <hi>Tantamont</hi> to a perpetuall abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition for all and every one in both houſes having abjured E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52046:51"/>by ſolemne oath and Covenant, the Parliament was in no hazard of agreing with the King to re-erect the fallen chaires of the Bishops: ſo there remained no other, but that either his Majeſtie should come over to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by his not agreing with them, yet really to agree with them in the perpetuall abolition of Epiſcopacy, ſince the conceſſion was for the laying Bishops aſide ever, till hee and his houſes had agreed upon a ſettled order for the Church. If this be not a full and formall enough conſent to the ordinance of changing the former Lawes anent praelat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, his Majeſtie, who now is, eaſily may and readily would ſupply all ſuch defects: if ſome of the faction did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, for their own evill intereſts, whiſper in his eares pernicious counſel, as our Warner in this place alſo doeth by frighting the King in conſcience from any ſuch conſent, for this end he caſts out a diſcourſe, the ſinshews whereof are in theſe three Epiſcopall maximes.
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats would flatter the King into a Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> Firſt that the legiſlative power is ſollie in the King, that is according to his Brethrens Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentary, that the Parliament is but the Kings great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of free choyce, without or againſt whoſe votes hee may make or unmake what Lawes he thinks expedient; but for them to make any ordinance for changing without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of any thing that has been, or inſtituting any new thing, or for them to defend this their legall right and cuſtome (time out of mind) againſt the armes of the Malignant party, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may deny it to be plaine rebellion.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <note place="margin">The prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats takes to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a negative voice in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> That the King and Parliament both together cannot make a Law, to the praejudice of Bishops without their own conſent, they being the third order of the Kingdome: for albeit it be ſacriledge in the Lords and Commons, to clame any the ſmalleſt share of the legiſlative power, (this in them were to pyck the chiefeſt jewel out of the Kings Crowne) yet this muſt be the due priviledge of the Bishops, they muſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:52046:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:52046:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:52046:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>be the third order of the Kingdome, yea the firſt and moſt high of the three, far above the other two temporall States of Lords and Commons; their share in the Legiſlative pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er muſt be ſo great, that neither King nor Parliament can paſſe any Law without their conſent, ſo that according to their humble proteſtation, all the Lawes and acts, which have been made by King and Parliament, ſince they were expelled the houſe of Lords, are cleerly voide and null.</p>
            <p>That the King and Parliament in diveſting Bishops of their temporall honour and eſtats,
<note place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats grieve that Monks and Friers, the Pope and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals were eaſten out of England by Henry the eight.</note> in abolishing their places in the Church, doe ſin more againſt conſcience then did <hi>Henry</hi> the eight and his Parliament, when they put down the Abbots and the Fryers. Wee muſt beleeve that <hi>Henry</hi> the eight his abolishing the order of Monks was one of the acts of his greateſt Tyranny and greed: wee muſt not doubt, but according to Law and reaſon, Abbots and priours ought to have kept ſtill their vote in Parliament, that the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes and Nunryes should have ſtood in their integrity, that the King and Parliament did wrong in caſting them down, and that now they ought in conſcience to be ſet up againe, yea that <hi>Henry</hi> the eight againſt all reaſon and conſcience did renounce his due obedience to the Pope, the Patriarch of the Weſt; the firſt Bishop of the univerſe, to whom the ſuperinſpection and government of the whole Catholick Church in all reaſon doth belong. Though all this be heere glaunced at by the Warner, and elſewhere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prove it to be the declared mind of his Brethren, yet we muſt be pardoned not to accept them as undenyable principles of cleare demonſtrations.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſupremacy of Kings is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt ground of the Doctors demonſtration is, that the covenant is ane oath to ſet up the Presbyterian govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in England at it is in Scotland and that this is contrary to the oath of Supremacy; for the oath of Supremacy makes
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:52046:53"/>the King the only ſupreame head and governour of the Church of England, that is, the civil head to ſee that every man doe his duty in his calling; alſo it gives the King a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power over all perſons in all cauſes: but the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is a politicall papacie, acknowledging no governours but only the Presbyters: it gives the King power over all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſubjects, but none at all in Eccleſiaſtick cauſes. Anſ. Is there in all this reaſoning any thing ſound? Firſt what article of the covenant beares the ſetting up of the Presbyterian government in England as it is in Scotland? II. If the oath of ſupremacy import no more then what the Warners expreſſe words are here, that the King is a civil head, to ſee every man doe his duty in his calling, let him be aſſured that no Presbyterian in Scotland was ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that ſupremacy. III. That the Presbytery is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and that a politicall one, the Warner knowes it ought not to be graunted upon his bare word. IV. That in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land no other governors are acknowledged then Presbyters, himſelfe contradicts in the very nixt words, where he tells that the Scots Presbytery aſcribes to the King a power over all perſons as ſubjects. V. That any Presbyterian in Scotland makes it ſacriledge to give the King any power at all in any Eccleſiaſtick cauſe; it is a ſenſeleſſe untruth.</p>
            <p>The Warners arguments are not more idle and weake,
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vanity.</note> then his triumphing upon them is inſolent: for he concludes from theſe wiſe and ſtrong demonſtrations, that the poor covenant is apparently deceitfull, unvalide, impious, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and what not? yea that all the learned divines in Europe wil conclude it ſo, &amp; that all the covenanters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfes who have any ingenuity, muſt grant this much; and that no knowing English man can deny it, but his owne conſcience will give him thely. Anſ. If the Warner with any ſeriouſneſſe hath weighed this part of his owne write, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:52046:54"/>if his mind goe along with his pen, I may without great preſumption pronounce his judgment to be none of the moſt ſolide.</p>
            <p>His following vapours being full of aire we let them eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish, only while he mentioneth our charging the King with intentions of changing the Religion and government, we anſwer, that we have been moſt willing alwayes to aſcribe to the King good intentions but withall we have long avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed that the praelaticall party have gone beyond intentions to manifeſt by printed declarations and publick actions their former deſigne to bring Tiranny upon the States, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery upon the Churches of all the three Kingdomes: and that this very write of the Warners makes it evident, that this ſame minde yet remaines within them without the leaſt shew of repentance. So long as the conſcience of the court is mannaged by men of ſuch principles, it is not poſſible to free the hearts of the moſt underſtanding, from a great deale of Jealouſy and feare to have Religion and lawes ſtill over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by that factione.</p>
            <p>But the Warner commands us,
<note place="margin">The cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is not for propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of Religion by armes.</note> to ſpeake to his <hi>Dilemma,</hi> whither we think it lawfull or unlawfull for ſubjects to take armes againſt their prince meerly for Religion. We anſwer, that the reaſons whereby he thinks to conclude againſt us, on both ſides are very poor, if we shall ſay, it is unlawfull; then he makes us to condemne our ſelfes, becauſe our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant teſtifies to the world, that we have taken up armes meerly to alter Religion, and that we beare no alleadgance to our King but in order to Religion, which in plaine tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes is to our owne humours and conceits. Anſ. There be many untruthes here in few words, firſt how much reality and truth the Warner and ſome of his fellowes beleeves to be in that thing which they call Religion, their owne heart knowes; but it can be no great charity in him to make the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:52046:54"/>Religion of all covenanters to be nothing but their owne humours and conceits. Secondly it is not true that Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beare no alleadgance to the King but only in order to religion. III. The Parliament of England denied that they took up armes againſt their King, though to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the popish praelaticall and malignant faction, who were about to deſtroy them with armes. IV. They have declared, that their purpoſe was not at all, to alter Religion but to purge it from the corruptions of Bishops and ceremonies that to long had been noxious unto them. V. They have oft profeſſed that their armes were taken for the defence of their juſt liberties, whereof the preſervation and reformation of Religion was but one.</p>
            <p>The other horne of his <hi>Dilemma</hi> is as blunt in pushing as the former. If we make it lawfull (ſaith he) to take up armes for Religion, we then juſtify the independents and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts; wee make way for any that will plant what ever they apprehend to be true Religion by force, and to cut the throat of all Magiſtrats, who are in a contrary opinion to them; that it is a ridiculous partiality for any to priviledge their own Religion as truth and Goſpell. Anſ.
<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners black Atheiſme.</note> Whether will theſe men goe at laſt, the ſtrength of this reaſon is blak atheiſme, that their is no realty of truth in any Religion, that no man may be permitted to take his Religion for any thing more but his owne apprehenſion, which without ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous folly he muſt not praeferre to any other mans appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a contrary Religion: this is much worſe then the pagane Scepticiſme, which turned all reality of truth into a meer apprehenſion of truth, wherein their was no certainty at all: this not only turnes the moſt certaine truths, even theſe divine ones of Religion, into meer uncertaine concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but which is worſe, it wil have the moſt orthodoxe beleever ſo to think, ſpeake and act, as if the opinions of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:52046:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:52046:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:52046:56"/>Independents, Anabaptiſts, Turks, Jews, Pagans or groſſe Atheiſts were as good, true and ſolide as the beleefe of <hi>Moyſes</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> were of the truths revealed to them from heaven. Secondly we ſay that ſubjects defence of their Religion and liberties eſtablished by Law, againſt the violent uſurpation of Papiſts, Praelats or Malignants, is not the planting of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by arms; much leſſe is it the cutting of the throats of al Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats who differ in any point of Religion.
<note n="a" place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the defenſive armes of the Dutch &amp; Frensh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> III. In the judgement of the praelaticall party, the defenſive armes of the Proteſtants in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> muſt be als much condemned as the offenſive armes of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts in <hi>Munſter,</hi> or of the ſectaries this day in <hi>England.</hi> Can theſe men dreame that the World for their pleaſure will ſo farre diveſt themſelves of all Religion and reaſon, as to take from their hands ſo brutish and Atheiſticall maximes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats decline the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of counſels.</note> He concluds with a wish of a generall counſel, at leaſt of all proteſtant Churches for to condemne all broatchers of ſeditious principles. Anſ. All true covenanters goe before him in that deſire, being confident that he and his fellowes as they have declined al ready the moſt ſolemne aſſemblies of their owne countries, upon aſſurance of their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo their tergiverſation would be als great, if they were to anſwer to an oecumenick Synod.
<note n="c" place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> What (I pray) would the Warner ſay in a counſel of proteſtants for the practiſe of his party pointed at in his laſt words? I meane their purging the Pope of <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> of purpoſe to make way for a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, yea for a returne to <hi>Rome,</hi> as this day it lyes under the wings of the Pope and Cardinals.
<note n="d" place="margin">The Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats are ſtil perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the King and all his Kingdoms if they may not be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> Alſo what could they anſwer in a Chriſtian counſel unto this charge, which is the drift of this whole Book, that they are ſo farre from any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe for all the blood and miſery, which their wickednes (moſt) has brought on the former King and all his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes theſe eleven yeares, that rather then they had not
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:52046:56"/>the Covenant and generall aſſembly in Scotland deſtroyed as an Idoll and Antichriſt, they wil chuſe yet ſtill to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyle all in new calamities? This King alſo and his whole Family, the remainder of the blood and Eſtats in all the three Kingdomes, muſt be hazarded for the ſowing together of the torne mytres, and the reerecting of the fallen chayres of Praelats. If Bishops muſt lie ſtill in their deſerved ruines, they perſeveer in their peremptory reſolution, to have their burials ſprinckled with the ashes of the royall Family and all the three Kingdomes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:52046:57"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOod Reader, the Authors abſence from the Preſſe the whole time of the impreſſion, and the Printers unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the English language, has occaſioned not onely many miſpunctations and literall faults, but alſo diverſe groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Errata ſuch as the following which thou art intreated to mend with thy Pen:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 4. <hi>lin.</hi> 23. <hi>for had read hath. pag.</hi> 9. <hi>lin.</hi> 8. <hi>for Provincio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall read Provinciall. p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 30 <hi>for whereby r. where. p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>for pairt r. part. p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 19, <hi>for can r. doth. l.</hi> 30. <hi>for pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant r. Proteſtant. pag.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>for theſe r. the. p.</hi> 23. <hi>l. ult. for over r. or. for truſted r. truſtee. p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>for impatien, t r. impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. l.</hi> 18. <hi>dele, and. p.</hi> 28. <hi>in marg. for commiſſarie r. commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. l.</hi> 14. <hi>for and r. or. l.</hi> 29. <hi>for chardge r. charge. p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>for chardges r. charges. l.</hi> 25. <hi>for citation r. irritation. p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>for praecipies r. praecipices. p.</hi> 35. <hi>in tit. of chap.</hi> 7. <hi>for paritie r. part. p.</hi> 36. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>for ſcandals r. ſcandal. p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>for benefite r. benefice. p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>for nation r. ſouldier. l.</hi> 11. <hi>for their ſouls r. his ſoule. p.</hi> 48. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>dele Anſ. p.</hi> 49. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>for Warner r. Doctor. p.</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>for the r. his. p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>for treaſure r. Bishop. p.</hi> 55. <hi>in tit. of chap.</hi> 9. <hi>for their r. the. p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 31. <hi>for Chriſt r. Chriſt his. l.</hi> 32. <hi>for point blank to r. point blanck. contrare to. p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>dele and. l.</hi> 1. <hi>for unpoureth r. vapoureth l.</hi> 17. <hi>for where r. heere. p.</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>for continues r. continue. l.</hi> 6. <hi>for are r. is. p.</hi> 66. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>for to r. ſo. l.</hi> 9. <hi>for warned. r. warmed. p.</hi> 67. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>for in. r. to. p.</hi> 68. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>for or. r. which. l.</hi> 16. <hi>for laſt. r. nixt. p.</hi> 70. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>for leſt. r. beſt. l. ult. for null the Church and r. the verie being of. p.</hi> 71. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>for Reformed r. Reformed Churches. p.</hi> 73. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>for charge r. chaire. p.</hi> 74. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>for ſervice r. ſervice book. l.</hi> 28. <hi>dele, and. p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>dele, and to the gift. p.</hi> 76. <hi>l. ult. for haths. r. hath. p.</hi> 78. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>for doſzen r. dozen. p.</hi> 82. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>for inprints. r. imprints. p.</hi> 84. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>for complanit r. complaint. p.</hi> 85. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>for aſide ever r. aſide for ever. l.</hi> 16. <hi>for ſinshews r. ſinews.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
